<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Purpose on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/purpose/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Purpose on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2025 08:29:18 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/purpose/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday Mantra: Nothing meaningful without discomfort</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/mantra-discomfort/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2025 08:29:18 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/mantra-discomfort/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We spend &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of our time trying to avoid pain, effort, and discomfort. In the PhD, this can take a myriad shapes: reading too much literature (rather than writing our own ideas), &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; reading a competitor researcher&amp;rsquo;s latest paper (it may render our work unoriginal), doing email first (vs. that hard, laborious qualitative data analysis), making a research plan with concrete deadlines (accountability, yikes!), asking questions at a research seminar (will we look dumb?), delaying reaching out to potential participants in our research (cold-contacting strangers is awkward, right?), meeting our supervisors&amp;hellip; Then, one day, we realize that avoiding discomfort is &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; the opposite of what makes the PhD a meaningful endeavor. This post delves deeper into that realization, deriving a &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-1/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;mantra&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; to support us during hard times in the doctoral journey.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forget New Year&#39;s resolutions -- Do a Yearly Review instead</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/yearly-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jan 2022 12:13:04 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/yearly-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are like most of us, by now (end of February) your New Year&amp;rsquo;s resolutions will have fallen by the wayside. In recent years, I have stopped doing resolutions altogether. This post is about what I do now instead, heeding the advice of productivity systems and psychotherapy approaches: &lt;strong&gt;a yearly review&lt;/strong&gt;. This post goes over my particular yearly review process, and how it can give your research motivation (and satisfaction with life) a yearly boost.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Micro-breaks and two Monday Mantras to supercharge them</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/micro-break-mantras/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2020 16:29:18 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/micro-break-mantras/</guid>
      <description>When we are writing a research paper, we need to find long stretches of focused time to get that writing done. Yet, even if we find them, can we really sustain intense focus during two or more hours? Today&amp;rsquo;s post looks at a research-backed and often overlooked tool in our productivity toolbox: the micro-break. To top it up, I provide two &amp;ldquo;monday mantras&amp;rdquo; to make your micro-breaks even more effective.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab series</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 16:59:14 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-series/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this blog I have often covered the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/&#34;&gt;mental health&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;wellbeing problems&lt;/a&gt; that may come with doing a PhD, if we are not careful. In this series of posts I look at the flip side of that, diving into the research on &lt;em&gt;thriving&lt;/em&gt; at work, to find out which practices may help us be a little happier during our research, and how to diagnose ourselves about what aspects of our research activity can most be improved.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 2: Purpose</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2019 09:45:01 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Continuing with last week&amp;rsquo;s post on &amp;ldquo;happiness at work&amp;rdquo;, in this post I explore the first of the four pillars for a happier workplace: the sense that your work has a &lt;em&gt;purpose&lt;/em&gt;, that it is personally meaningful to you. Read on to learn to self-assess your sense of purpose at work, and get some ideas on how to make your research work feel more meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>