<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Habits on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/habits/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Habits on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 18:14:20 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/habits/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Chronobiology addendum: A neurobiologist&#39;s guide to a healthy and productive day</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chronobiology-addendum/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 18:14:20 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chronobiology-addendum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In previous posts, we have seen &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chronobiology/&#34;&gt;how chronotype can influence our productivity&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chrono-breaks/&#34;&gt;how we can tweak our breaks&lt;/a&gt; to make the most of the ebbs and flows of our daily energy. But, how exactly can we use this chronobiology knowledge to craft a daily routine that is both productive and healthy, and fitting to our particular situation? In this post, I borrow from the habits and routines of an expert on the topic (Stanford neurobiologist Andrew Huberman) ten easy protocols you can put in practice to make every day your best day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD tool: Map out your PhD</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/map-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 18:32:52 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/map-thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We know that &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/&#34;&gt;steady everyday progress&lt;/a&gt; is a crucial factor in finishing a PhD. In previous posts, we have seen &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/&#34;&gt;productivity&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/to-do-list-overwhelm/&#34;&gt;techniques&lt;/a&gt; to support us in taking more of these daily steps. Yet, a lot of walking does not necessarily get us anywhere. We need to know that we are actually getting past key reference points, closer to our final destination. In this post, I propose a diagramming exercise to map out key obstacles, milestones and the &amp;ldquo;everyday fuel&amp;rdquo; that propels us past them in our journey towards PhD completion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>