<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Depression on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/depression/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Depression on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Sep 2021 13:44:49 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/depression/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Quickie: How many PhD students are anxious or depressed (or will drop out) worldwide?</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-many-phd-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Sep 2021 13:44:49 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-many-phd-students/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the catalysts that kickstarted this blog was the realization that &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;PhD students are at a higher risk of mental health problems&lt;/a&gt; than other students and professionals. Yet, how bad is the problem really? Exactly how many PhD students are &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/am-i-normal/&#34;&gt;suffering&lt;/a&gt; from depression or severe anxiety &lt;em&gt;right now&lt;/em&gt;? How many will &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/drop-out-phd/&#34;&gt;drop out&lt;/a&gt;? In this quickie post, I pull from the data of a few recent studies to give a concrete, numeric &lt;del&gt;answer&lt;/del&gt; guesstimate to these questions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Risk factors for depression and anxiety in doing a Ph.D.</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a follow-up to &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;the first post in this blog&lt;/a&gt;, I dig a little deeper in some of the research on anxiety and depression during doctoral studies, to find &amp;ldquo;risk factors&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;correlates&amp;rdquo; that seem to often come along these depressive symptoms. I hope that the awareness of these factors (from gender to other things you can actually change in your everyday life) will help you understand why some people struggle doing a PhD, while for others it seems a piece of cake. Change what you do and put the odds on your side!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is doing a Ph.D. bad... for your mental wellbeing?</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 15:47:47 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a growing body of research that indicates that doing a doctoral dissertation can be taxing on the mental health of PhD students, with depression, anxiety, or burnout as potential pitfalls. Is this problem real and, if so, how bad is it? In this post, I review several recent studies, some of which also offer insights about potential risk factors. This also kickstarts the whole idea of this blog, as a way to increase awareness about these difficulties, and offer practical tips and tricks to survive such a difficult period.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>