<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mindset on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/mindset/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mindset on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 10:40:14 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/mindset/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Productivity as Avoidance, or How *Not* to Think about Doctoral Productivity (book extract)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/productivity-avoidance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 10:40:14 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/productivity-avoidance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are a doctoral student struggling to move your dissertation forward, especially in the face of additional jobs, teaching, family, or other obligations, the thought of becoming more productive can be very appealing &amp;ndash; to the point of becoming a sort of obsession. After our review of (somewhat caricaturesque) &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-productivity-bad/&#34;&gt;doctoral productivity and anti-productivity arguments&lt;/a&gt;, in this post I summarize some of the ideas in Oliver Burkeman&amp;rsquo;s recent book, &lt;em&gt;Four thousand weeks&lt;/em&gt;, which I have found very helpful to reach a balance between my own productivity obsessions and the abandoning of all hope of being any good at my daily research activities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tiny idea: To-do lists are menus</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-menus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2024 10:13:12 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-menus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Overwhelmed by your endless to-do list? Stressed because of the many PhD-related tasks you need to &amp;ldquo;go through&amp;rdquo;? As &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/to-do-list-overwhelm/&#34;&gt;we discussed previously in the blog&lt;/a&gt;, you are not alone (and ask any already-doctors whether this feeling goes away after graduation). Lately, as I struggle with not-so-new-parenthood-unproductivity in my own research, I have been reminded several times of a mental reframe I first encountered in productivity writer &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oliverburkeman.com/&#34;&gt;Oliver Burkeman&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s work. This simple metaphor helped me change my relationship with my to-do list, without hurting my productivity (more probably, the opposite).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>