<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Learning on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Learning on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Jan 2022 12:13:04 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Forget New Year&#39;s resolutions -- Do a Yearly Review instead</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/yearly-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jan 2022 12:13:04 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/yearly-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are like most of us, by now (end of February) your New Year&amp;rsquo;s resolutions will have fallen by the wayside. In recent years, I have stopped doing resolutions altogether. This post is about what I do now instead, heeding the advice of productivity systems and psychotherapy approaches: &lt;strong&gt;a yearly review&lt;/strong&gt;. This post goes over my particular yearly review process, and how it can give your research motivation (and satisfaction with life) a yearly boost.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Big PhD questions: Should I do a PhD?</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/should-i-do/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 15:21:05 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/should-i-do/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are reading this, chances are that you have already decided to do a PhD. Yet, you may know someone who is considering a doctoral degree (or you may be offering such a position as a supervisor to prospective students). This post is for &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt;. In this new type of post, we will look at big questions facing any PhD student. Today, we analyze the question that precedes all the other big PhD questions: &amp;ldquo;should I do a PhD?&amp;rdquo;. Below, I offer a couple of quick, simple ways to look at this important life decision, and a list of 10 factors to consider when offered (or seeking) a PhD position.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Journaling for the doctorate (II): How to journal effectively</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/journaling-tips/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 12:45:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/journaling-tips/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Journaling during your doctorate can have a &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/journaling-benefits/&#34;&gt;host of benefits&lt;/a&gt; (for self-knowledge, mental and physical health). However, not everyone will benefit to the same degree, and different kinds of journaling have different advantages&amp;hellip; if done correctly over a sustained period of time. In this post, I will go over different research-backed journaling exercises and tips to make your journaling most effective.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Productivity tip: How I do weekly reviews</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/weekly-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2019 12:54:50 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/weekly-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Despite the emphasis I have made so far in developing productive and healthy everyday routines (from &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/to-do-list-overwhelm/&#34;&gt;to-do lists&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/&#34;&gt;pomodoros&lt;/a&gt;), not everything about productivity happens at this tactical, day-to-day level. In this short post, I guide you through what I think is the centerpiece of my own personal productivity system: the weekly review.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>