<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>http://ahappyphd.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 09:59:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ahappyphd.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 09:59:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/contact/</guid>
      <description>Please leave your comments, suggestions (for posts or about the blog), etc. in the form below, or email me at ahappyphd.blog@gmail.com. You can also let me know there if you want to be notified when I officially launch the blog.
Your NameEmail AddressAn email address is required.Message</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 17:11:44 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Being a Ph.D. student and being happy sometimes feel like two incompatible states. We know of factors that affect your wellbeing, like your supervisor style or whether you have financial support. Yet, is there anything that you can actually do to make your worklife better, once the ball is rolling? In this post, I reuse research about &amp;ldquo;happiness at work&amp;rdquo; to propose actions and routines to help you cross the PhD desert with a (bigger) smile on your face.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Supervision styles... and their consequences</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/supervision-styles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 17:11:31 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/supervision-styles/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Is your supervisor ignoring you? or maybe overwhelming you with tasks and feedback? is that how s/he perceives it? Supervision style is one of the factors that seem to affect most PhD students&amp;rsquo; mental wellbeing. However, we tend to take it for granted, as just a small quirk of our environment. In this post I go through some of the research on supervision styles and PhD student wellbeing and success. I also share a few things you might try in order to make your student/supervisor relationship a bit less&amp;hellip; bumpy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keeping organized: a brief review of productivity systems</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/review-productivity-systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 17:11:17 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/review-productivity-systems/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a Ph.D. student you have plenty to keep track of: course sessions and deadlines, reading papers, writing papers, submitting papers, designing studies, gathering data, analyzing or reporting it&amp;hellip; As an advisor, you may remember with nostalgia the blissful time when you were a PhD and had only one research line. How can anyone stay on top of this insurmountable pile of deadlines and to-dos? It turns out, many people have faced this problem before, and have came up with systematic ways of solving it. Over the years, I have tried quite a few of these systems and variations (and I still experiment!). In this post, I will give you the gist of some of them, and the pros and cons that I have found by using them in real (academic) life. But, as they often say, &amp;ldquo;your mileage may vary&amp;rdquo;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD tool: pitching your research with NABC</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/pitching-nabc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 17:10:54 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/pitching-nabc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a Ph.D. student, you are very often asked to present what your research is about. You may have to do it very shortly in the archetypal &amp;ldquo;elevator pitch&amp;rdquo; to a visiting professor. Or whenever you have to give a talk at a conference or doctoral consortium. In this post, I go over a technique that the president of a large US research lab pointed me to. I will walk you through its simple four-part structure, including some real examples from my own work. Don&amp;rsquo;t be fooled by its simplicity&amp;hellip; simplicity is its main strength!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Will you drop out of the PhD? or should you?</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/drop-out-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 17:10:15 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/drop-out-phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Aside from the fact that doing a PhD seems to put you at a greater risk of being anxious or depressed, there is also the issue of whether you will finish your thesis at all. In this post I dig a bit into studies that look not only at the drop-out rates of PhD studies - also what factors and issues seem to make dropping out more likely. Do not give up&amp;hellip; unless you really want to.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to choose a conference/journal for your papers</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/choosing-conference-journal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 17:09:56 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/choosing-conference-journal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sending papers to the wrong scientific venue is one of the most common causes for rejection I see every day. I choose my audience as one of the first steps in my process for writing papers. But, how do you do that exactly? Based on impact? Quality? Who&amp;rsquo;s the editor or chair? In this post, I go over steps and criteria that I use to find out where to send a particular piece of research work. Never go very far in the writing without a clear idea about this!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I write papers</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 17:09:39 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is plenty of advice out there on how to write academic publications, from general stylistic tips to very field-specific guides. Yet, I&amp;rsquo;ve found most of that advice tends to be abstract, never giving you a step-by-step account of the process. In this post, I share the process to I find myself using after 50+ academic publications. This will give you an idea of where to start writing your paper (especially if you have never written one), and will show you that all polished papers have humble (even crappy) origins. Kill perfectionism, and the dreaded &amp;ldquo;academic writer&amp;rsquo;s block&amp;rdquo; will fade away.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Risk factors for depression and anxiety in doing a Ph.D.</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 17:09:16 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a follow-up to &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;the first post in this blog&lt;/a&gt;, I dig a little deeper in some of the research on anxiety and depression during doctoral studies, to find &amp;ldquo;risk factors&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;correlates&amp;rdquo; that seem to often come along these depressive symptoms. I hope that the awareness of these factors (from gender to other things you can actually change in your everyday life) will help you understand why some people struggle doing a PhD, while for others it seems a piece of cake. Change what you do and put the odds on your side!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The second reason why I write this blog</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/second-reason/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 17:09:05 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/second-reason/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Initially, I thought that I was doing this to help the PhD students around me (and others like them elsewhere) to pass through the dissertation process more effectively, with less stress. But at some point, I realized that other, more selfish, reasons were playing out as well. In this personal account I reflect on a chronic problem of academics and Ph.D. students alike, and how I face it through this blog.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Productivity tip: the Pomodoro technique</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 17:08:53 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most basic, flexible and effective productivity techniques, which I&amp;rsquo;ve been using for many years.  I know many PhD students and academics that swear by it, but I am still surprised by others who do not know about it. In this post I come back to its origins, how to do it, and how I have combined it with other routines to keep me on track. Essential in this age of smartphones, social media and other constant distractions!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD tool: The CQOCE diagram</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/cqoce-diagram/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 16:22:33 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/cqoce-diagram/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By far, this is the tool (as in, &amp;ldquo;thinking tool&amp;rdquo;) which I recommend most often to PhD students. This diagram summarizes your main research questions, thesis contributions and evidence of their usefulness. While painful to make, this brutal synthesis exercise is also a powerful communication tool. In this post, I explain how it works, its origins, and how making 18+ versions of it helped me through my PhD. Copy the provided template and use it in your PhD supervision meetings or even in the PhD defense!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is doing a Ph.D. bad... for your mental wellbeing?</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 15:47:47 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a growing body of research that indicates that doing a doctoral dissertation can be taxing on the mental health of PhD students, with depression, anxiety, or burnout all on the table. Is this problem real and, if so, how bad is it? In this post, I review several recent studies, some of which also offer insights about potential risk factors. This also kickstarts the whole idea of this blog, as a way to increase awareness about these difficulties, and offer practical tips and tricks to survive such a difficult period.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 15:41:55 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/about/</guid>
      <description>About A Happy PhD Are you doing a doctoral dissertation and feeling a bit lost, or unworthy, or just not knowing where to start, how to order your ideas and work effectively? Do you feel like everyone else is finding their path &amp;ldquo;naturally&amp;rdquo;, but you don&amp;rsquo;t?
Are you supervising doctoral students, but feel like you are basically &amp;ldquo;improvising&amp;rdquo;, or following whatever behaviors your advisors applied with you, and wonder why nobody teaches you how to do this, why there is no handbook on how to give effective advice?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>