<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>http://ahappyphd.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 09:59:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ahappyphd.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 09:59:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/contact/</guid>
      <description>Please leave your comments, suggestions (for posts or about the blog), etc. in the form below, or email me at ahappyphd.blog@gmail.com. You can also let me know there if you want to be notified when I officially launch the blog.
Your NameEmail AddressAn email address is required.Message</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is doing a Ph.D. bad... for your mental wellbeing?</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 15:47:47 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a growing body of research that indicates that doing a doctoral dissertation can be taxing on the mental health of PhD students, with depression, anxiety, or burnout as potential pitfalls. Is this problem real and, if so, how bad is it? In this post, I review several recent studies, some of which also offer insights about potential risk factors. This also kickstarts the whole idea of this blog, as a way to increase awareness about these difficulties, and offer practical tips and tricks to survive such a difficult period.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 15:41:55 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/about/</guid>
      <description>About A Happy PhD Are you doing a doctoral dissertation and feeling a bit lost, or unworthy, or just not knowing where to start, how to order your ideas and work effectively? Do you feel like everyone else is finding their path &amp;ldquo;naturally&amp;rdquo;, but you don&amp;rsquo;t?
Are you supervising doctoral students, but feel like you are basically &amp;ldquo;improvising&amp;rdquo;, or following whatever behaviors your advisors applied with you, and wonder why nobody teaches you how to do this, why there is no handbook on how to give effective advice?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>