<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Decision on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/decision/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Decision on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 10:33:53 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/decision/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tiny idea: Use the Regret Test for daily decision-making</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-regret/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 10:33:53 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-regret/</guid>
      <description>Have you ever spent an hour scrolling on Instagram (or your ​social media addiction of choice​) and later realized with a pang of regret that such a time could have been spent much better doing something else you deeply ​value​? This sort of realization is at the core of this week&amp;rsquo;s blog post: a tiny practice to guide our daily decision making about what to do next. This idea will also be familiar to long-time newsletter subscribers, as it was an early “newsletter exclusive”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intervision: Unblocking yourself... with a little help from some friends</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/intervision/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2022 16:45:22 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/intervision/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a PhD (and as doctoral supervisors) we often face situations where we feel blocked, with no idea of how to get out  or what to do next. In this post, the first of a series distilling wisdom from the latest round of &amp;ldquo;A Happy PhD&amp;rdquo; workshops, we look at a peer advice technique we have repeatedly use in the workshops to help students (and supervisors!) unblock. All you need is&amp;hellip; a little help from a small group of people.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Big PhD questions: Should I do a PhD?</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/should-i-do/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 15:21:05 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/should-i-do/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are reading this, chances are that you have already decided to do a PhD. Yet, you may know someone who is considering a doctoral degree (or you may be offering such a position as a supervisor to prospective students). This post is for &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt;. In this new type of post, we will look at big questions facing any PhD student. Today, we analyze the question that precedes all the other big PhD questions: &amp;ldquo;should I do a PhD?&amp;rdquo;. Below, I offer a couple of quick, simple ways to look at this important life decision, and a list of 10 factors to consider when offered (or seeking) a PhD position.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More effective group decision-making meetings</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/meeting-pattern/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 23:26:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/meeting-pattern/</guid>
      <description>Have you ever gone out of a supposedly important meeting, after more than one hour of talking, but still feeling like a poor (or obvious) decision has been made? In this post, I go over a simple pattern to organize more effective meetings when a group decision or proposal has to be made. Don&amp;rsquo;t be fooled by its simplicity: it&amp;rsquo;s much more effective than &amp;ldquo;business as usual&amp;rdquo; meetings, but people (including ourselves) will resist it fiercely, because it feels unnatural to act against our internalized meeting routines.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making important decisions about the doctorate (II)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 11:59:28 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What can we do, when we have to take a hard decision about the PhD (like changing supervisors or leaving doctoral studies altogether) but we don&amp;rsquo;t really know which way to go? In the continuation to &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-1/&#34;&gt;last week&amp;rsquo;s post&lt;/a&gt;, we see how to go about the actual decision-making, to choose the option that has the best chances to satisfy us in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making important decisions about the doctorate (I)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 18:59:31 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the PhD (and beyond), we sometimes face a difficult situation, and we have to take a hard decision: do I leave my PhD? do I take an unrelated job to earn more money while I try to finish the PhD? do I seek a new supervisor that better supports me? do I accept the change of direction that my supervisor is suggesting? In this two-part post series, I will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; give the answer to those hard questions, but rather provide a decision &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; that can help us find the option that is right &lt;em&gt;for us&lt;/em&gt;, in our particular circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>