<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>COVID-19 on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>http://ahappyphd.org/tags/covid-19/</link>
    <description>Recent content in COVID-19 on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 09:04:40 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ahappyphd.org/tags/covid-19/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Am I normal? An intro to mental health in the doctorate</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/am-i-normal/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 09:04:40 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/am-i-normal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By now, we have established that PhD students (and academics in general) &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;seem to be at a higher risk to develop mental health problems&lt;/a&gt; like depression or chronic stress. But, how can we know if &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; have one of these mental health problems, right here, right now? In this post, co-authored with colleague, friend and therapist Paula Odriozola-González, we go over a few basic concepts of psychopathology, and propose criteria and simple practices to help separate internal experiences that we all go through at one time or another, from the more serious stuff.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to be a PhD student</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-to-be/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 09:33:48 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-to-be/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Not a few of the people that read this blog, do so with a very clear outcome in mind: to finish their PhD, to get that damned piece of paper saying that they’re doctors. In this struggle, we (yes, I did that too) often forget that the PhD is more of a &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; (a learning, a practice) than it is an outcome. In this adaptation of a poem by Wendell Berry, I take a stab at what it took for me to become a researcher. I write this as much for you as for myself – to remind myself that, in a sense, we never cease to be students, we remain always beginners in the new knowledge that we (and others) create with our research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quickie: How to be more mindful</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-mindfulness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 14:11:06 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-mindfulness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As our time at home increases due to quarantines and lockdowns, so does our opportunity to endlessly gossip, procrastinate or bitch about the global situation, our leaders and celebrities, or the people we happen to live with. Or, we could choose to be productive. We could choose to develop a new skill. Being mindful allows us to notice, in a non-judgmental way, the richness of life in and around us (yes, even when you’re locked down at home day after day). In this new kind of post (the “quickie”), I give you in brief a few reasons to develop such mindfulness, and three ways to start learning that skill, &lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Monday Mantra for times of coronavirus</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2020 11:50:55 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the spread of the COVID-19 pandemic, and increasing restrictions on movement and other aspects of life, also come anxiety, fear and a strange sense of unreality. Doing anything related to your PhD seems unusually hard, or pointless… even dangerous, compared with being continuously in the lookout for the latest news or advice on what to do. In this post, I share a &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-1/&#34;&gt;mantra&lt;/a&gt; and a few other tips that I use to help myself stay sane and (kinda) productive in these difficult times.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>