<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Timeblocking on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/timeblocking/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Timeblocking on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 17:12:17 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/timeblocking/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How to restart our PhD habit after a productivity slump</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/restart-phd-habit/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 17:12:17 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/restart-phd-habit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A family member dies, or their health fails catastrophically, requiring intense caregiving. A workload spike at our thesis-unrelated job becomes  an ongoing plateau. Life&amp;rsquo;s logistics somehow magically align to get in the way, again and again. The experience of a &amp;ldquo;hair on fire&amp;rdquo; emergency morphing into a prolonged thesis progress slump is more common than we think. My recent hiatus from blogging has helped me see this common problem of doctoral students in a new light (and to experience it firsthand). This post explores mindsets and strategies that can help us return to making &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/&#34;&gt;regular progress&lt;/a&gt; on our non-urgent but important projects (a.k.a. the thesis).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defusing task conflict in the PhD</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/task-conflict/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 09:38:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/task-conflict/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As we saw &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/productivity-challenges/&#34;&gt;in a recent post&lt;/a&gt;, “task conflict” is a common productivity challenge of doctoral students. As PhD students, we often have to juggle different identities, priorities, jobs, projects… along with doing the thesis itself. Yet, so often, it is the thesis-related tasks that keep getting pushed back. In this post, I will go over tips, practices and techniques that might be useful if you find yourself struggling with this particular challenge in your PhD.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>