<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Communication on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/communication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Communication on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2022 01:14:56 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/communication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting into the weeds of writing</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/weeds-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2022 01:14:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/weeds-writing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you feel like the prose of your papers is burdensome and rambling, even after lots of &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers/&#34;&gt;outlining and feedback&lt;/a&gt;? Do you often get feedback from co-authors about it being ambiguous, aimless or vague? Do you keep making the same writing mistakes again and again? The final step in drafting a paper (generating final prose &lt;em&gt;and editing it&lt;/em&gt; sentence-by-sentence for clarity) is laborious and often overlooked. In this short post, I point you to a set of proofreading/editing tips from another blog, and share with you one tip to help you detect those pesky errors and make your prose more punchy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing exercise: sitting with uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/writing-uncertainty/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2020 16:57:21 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/writing-uncertainty/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever had this feeling, while writing, that your prose is leading nowhere? that right now it would be a great moment to defreeze the fridge? to check your phone, because someone may have texted? In this post, I offer a simple exercise to use next time these internal interruptions assail you during writing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing research papers series</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/writing-papers-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 16:59:00 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/writing-papers-series/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Writing research papers is one of the most dreaded (and most unavoidable) activities for many people during the PhD. In this series of posts I explore some of the reasons why writing research papers is difficult when one arrives at the PhD, and explain what concrete writing process I find myself following after more than a decade of academic writing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday Mantra: On scientific communication and research in general</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2019 19:35:02 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When we present our research to others, in a conference or in writing, we often feel insecure: is what I found obvious? is there a fatal flaw in my reasoning or my data analysis? will the audience finally &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impostor_syndrome&#34;&gt;unmask me as the impostor I am&lt;/a&gt;? This week&amp;rsquo;s short &amp;ldquo;Monday Mantra&amp;rdquo; goes at the heart of such unproductive self-talk. What is all this really about?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>