<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Research on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>http://ahappyphd.net/tags/research/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Research on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 17:09:56 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ahappyphd.net/tags/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How to choose a conference/journal for your papers</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.net/posts/choosing-conference-journal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 17:09:56 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.net/posts/choosing-conference-journal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sending papers to the wrong scientific venue is one of the most common causes for rejection I see every day. I choose my audience as one of the first steps in my process for writing papers. But, how do you do that exactly? Based on impact? Quality? Who&amp;rsquo;s the editor or chair? In this post, I go over steps and criteria that I use to find out where to send a particular piece of research work. Never go very far in the writing without a clear idea about this!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I write papers</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.net/posts/how-i-write-papers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 17:09:39 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.net/posts/how-i-write-papers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is plenty of advice out there on how to write academic publications, from general stylistic tips to very field-specific guides. Yet, I&amp;rsquo;ve found most of that advice tends to be abstract, never giving you a step-by-step account of the process. In this post, I share the process to I find myself using after 50+ academic publications. This will give you an idea of where to start writing your paper (especially if you have never written one), and will show you that all polished papers have humble (even crappy) origins. Kill perfectionism, and the dreaded &amp;ldquo;academic writer&amp;rsquo;s block&amp;rdquo; will fade away.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>