<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Progress on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>http://ahappyphd.org/tags/progress/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Progress on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 10:33:56 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ahappyphd.org/tags/progress/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>What kind of doctoral student are you? Motivational profiles and completing the PhD (Study report)</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/what-kind-phd-student/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 10:33:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/what-kind-phd-student/</guid>
      <description>Many factors seem to play out into whether we complete our PhD, or drop out of it. Some of them are external and largely uncontrollable (like financial or family problems), while others relate to our thesis project and motivation. In this new type of blog post (the &amp;ldquo;study report&amp;rdquo;), I dive into the results of a recent research study that defines five types of doctoral students, in terms of their motivational profile.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD tool: Map out your PhD</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/map-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 18:32:52 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/map-thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We know that &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/&#34;&gt;steady everyday progress&lt;/a&gt; is a crucial factor in finishing a PhD. In previous posts, we have seen &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/&#34;&gt;productivity&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/to-do-list-overwhelm/&#34;&gt;techniques&lt;/a&gt; to support us in taking more of these daily steps. Yet, a lot of walking does not necessarily get us anywhere. We need to know that we are actually getting past key reference points, closer to our final destination. In this post, I propose a diagramming exercise to map out key obstacles, milestones and the &amp;ldquo;everyday fuel&amp;rdquo; that propels us past them in our journey towards PhD completion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advising for progress: tips for PhD supervisors</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/advising-progress/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2020 09:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/advising-progress/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/&#34;&gt;a previous post&lt;/a&gt;, we have seen the crucial role that having a sense of progress plays, not only in the productivity, but also in the engagement and persistence of a PhD student towards the doctorate. While this recognition (and the practices to &amp;ldquo;make progress visible&amp;rdquo; we saw) put a big emphasis on the student as the main active agent, PhD students are not the only actors in this play. Is there anything that doctoral &lt;em&gt;supervisors&lt;/em&gt; can do to help? In this post, I go over some of the same management research on progress and our own evidence from the field, looking at what supervisors can do to support their students in perceiving continuous progress that eventually leads to a finished doctoral thesis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultivating the progress loop in your PhD</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 11:30:48 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt like you are &amp;ldquo;stuck&amp;rdquo; in your PhD, making no progress, or going in circles? If so, you are in good company &amp;ndash; most PhD students report such experience at one time or another during their doctoral process. The normalcy of this experience, however, should not make us dismiss it as unimportant. In this post I review research that speaks to the importance of this sense of progress (or the lack of it) to our engagement with work and the eventual completion (or dropping out) of the PhD. The post also reviews several everyday practices to cultivate your own sense of progress.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>