<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Progress on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/progress/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Progress on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2023 10:21:11 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/progress/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>ChatGPT&#39;s doctoral productivity advice... and four ideas the algorithm will (probably) not give you</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chatgpt-productivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2023 10:21:11 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chatgpt-productivity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We know that &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/&#34;&gt;making progress&lt;/a&gt; is a critical motivational factor in finishing a PhD &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; maintaining good mental health while we do it. In turn, our &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/tags/productivity/&#34;&gt;productivity&lt;/a&gt; plays a big role in whether we make progress on our dissertation or not. As the first post in a series on doctoral productivity, I could not help but fall into one of the &lt;em&gt;thèmes du jour&lt;/em&gt;: whether ChatGPT and similar artificial intelligence (AI) tools can write a good piece about this topic. In this post, I go over a couple of iterations of (pretty good) computationally-generated advice, and finally give you a few ideas that I think are overlooked by the algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A happy Master thesis: Progress and appropriation even before the PhD</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happy-master/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 08:15:13 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happy-master/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Feelings of being stuck, of not knowing where we’re going, self-doubt, guilt… are not exclusive to the doctoral thesis journey. Despite their smaller scope, other long projects with little feedback or structure (like a master thesis) share the same motivational pitfalls and may induce the same kind of uncomfortable experience at times. In this two-part post series, we review key advice and simple practices which could also be useful to help us face these capstone projects. But these can also be very useful if you are a PhD student just starting out!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intervision: Unblocking yourself... with a little help from some friends</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/intervision/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2022 16:45:22 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/intervision/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a PhD (and as doctoral supervisors) we often face situations where we feel blocked, with no idea of how to get out  or what to do next. In this post, the first of a series distilling wisdom from the latest round of &amp;ldquo;A Happy PhD&amp;rdquo; workshops, we look at a peer advice technique we have repeatedly use in the workshops to help students (and supervisors!) unblock. All you need is&amp;hellip; a little help from a small group of people.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Supporting different types of students to complete their PhD (Study report)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/supporting-types-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 08:50:08 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/supporting-types-phd/</guid>
      <description>Aside from PhD students&amp;rsquo; own motivational factors (e.g., how much progress they perceive, or how exhausted they are), the support they receive from supervisors is another key aspect related to doctoral completion. In the continuation of last week&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;study report&amp;rdquo;, we discuss how different kinds of supervisor support relate to those motivational factors and, eventually, the finishing of the doctorate. We will also see how supervisors could foster these motivational aspects and help their students complete the PhD.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What kind of doctoral student are you? Motivational profiles and completing the PhD (Study report)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/what-kind-phd-student/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 10:33:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/what-kind-phd-student/</guid>
      <description>Many factors seem to play out into whether we complete our PhD, or drop out of it. Some of them are external and largely uncontrollable (like financial or family problems), while others relate to our thesis project and motivation. In this new type of blog post (the &amp;ldquo;study report&amp;rdquo;), I dive into the results of a recent research study that defines five types of doctoral students, in terms of their motivational profile.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD tool: Map out your PhD</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/map-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 18:32:52 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/map-thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We know that &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/&#34;&gt;steady everyday progress&lt;/a&gt; is a crucial factor in finishing a PhD. In previous posts, we have seen &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/&#34;&gt;productivity&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/to-do-list-overwhelm/&#34;&gt;techniques&lt;/a&gt; to support us in taking more of these daily steps. Yet, a lot of walking does not necessarily get us anywhere. We need to know that we are actually getting past key reference points, closer to our final destination. In this post, I propose a diagramming exercise to map out key obstacles, milestones and the &amp;ldquo;everyday fuel&amp;rdquo; that propels us past them in our journey towards PhD completion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advising for progress: tips for PhD supervisors</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/advising-progress/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2020 09:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/advising-progress/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/&#34;&gt;a previous post&lt;/a&gt;, we have seen the crucial role that having a sense of progress plays, not only in the productivity, but also in the engagement and persistence of a PhD student towards the doctorate. While this recognition (and the practices to &amp;ldquo;make progress visible&amp;rdquo; we saw) put a big emphasis on the student as the main active agent, PhD students are not the only actors in this play. Is there anything that doctoral &lt;em&gt;supervisors&lt;/em&gt; can do to help? In this post, I go over some of the same management research on progress and our own evidence from the field, looking at what supervisors can do to support their students in perceiving continuous progress that eventually leads to a finished doctoral thesis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultivating the progress loop in your PhD</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 11:30:48 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt like you are &amp;ldquo;stuck&amp;rdquo; in your PhD, making no progress, or going in circles? If so, you are in good company &amp;ndash; most PhD students report such experience at one time or another during their doctoral process. The normalcy of this experience, however, should not make us dismiss it as unimportant. In this post I review research that speaks to the importance of this sense of progress (or the lack of it) to our engagement with work and the eventual completion (or dropping out) of the PhD. The post also reviews several everyday practices to cultivate your own sense of progress.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>