<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Career on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/career/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Career on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 10:50:36 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/career/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A PhD So Good It Can&#39;t Be Ignored (book extract) -- Passion, Practice, and Control</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/phd-so-good-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 10:50:36 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/phd-so-good-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A doctorate is typically the first step in a longer (academic or otherwise) research career. Many think of it as a grueling rite of passage one must endure to get the job they want later on. But are there ways we can do the PhD to set us up for a remarkable and satisfying career? Are there ways we can make the PhD journey itself feel like a &amp;ldquo;good job&amp;rdquo;? In the first part of this book extract, we draw lessons from Cal Newport&amp;rsquo;s book &lt;em&gt;So Good They Can&amp;rsquo;t Ignore You&lt;/em&gt;, about &amp;ldquo;passion traps&amp;rdquo;, we look at properties of a good PhD job, focusing on mastery, control, and how to develop them for a more satisfying PhD (and beyond).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Big PhD questions: Should I do a PhD?</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/should-i-do/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 15:21:05 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/should-i-do/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are reading this, chances are that you have already decided to do a PhD. Yet, you may know someone who is considering a doctoral degree (or you may be offering such a position as a supervisor to prospective students). This post is for &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt;. In this new type of post, we will look at big questions facing any PhD student. Today, we analyze the question that precedes all the other big PhD questions: &amp;ldquo;should I do a PhD?&amp;rdquo;. Below, I offer a couple of quick, simple ways to look at this important life decision, and a list of 10 factors to consider when offered (or seeking) a PhD position.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making important decisions about the doctorate (II)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 11:59:28 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What can we do, when we have to take a hard decision about the PhD (like changing supervisors or leaving doctoral studies altogether) but we don&amp;rsquo;t really know which way to go? In the continuation to &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-1/&#34;&gt;last week&amp;rsquo;s post&lt;/a&gt;, we see how to go about the actual decision-making, to choose the option that has the best chances to satisfy us in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making important decisions about the doctorate (I)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 18:59:31 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the PhD (and beyond), we sometimes face a difficult situation, and we have to take a hard decision: do I leave my PhD? do I take an unrelated job to earn more money while I try to finish the PhD? do I seek a new supervisor that better supports me? do I accept the change of direction that my supervisor is suggesting? In this two-part post series, I will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; give the answer to those hard questions, but rather provide a decision &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; that can help us find the option that is right &lt;em&gt;for us&lt;/em&gt;, in our particular circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>