<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Happiness on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/happiness/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Happiness on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2025 08:29:18 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/happiness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday Mantra: Nothing meaningful without discomfort</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/mantra-discomfort/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2025 08:29:18 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/mantra-discomfort/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We spend &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of our time trying to avoid pain, effort, and discomfort. In the PhD, this can take a myriad shapes: reading too much literature (rather than writing our own ideas), &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; reading a competitor researcher&amp;rsquo;s latest paper (it may render our work unoriginal), doing email first (vs. that hard, laborious qualitative data analysis), making a research plan with concrete deadlines (accountability, yikes!), asking questions at a research seminar (will we look dumb?), delaying reaching out to potential participants in our research (cold-contacting strangers is awkward, right?), meeting our supervisors&amp;hellip; Then, one day, we realize that avoiding discomfort is &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; the opposite of what makes the PhD a meaningful endeavor. This post delves deeper into that realization, deriving a &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-1/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;mantra&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; to support us during hard times in the doctoral journey.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tiny practice: Boost your workday happiness with natural spaces</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-natural/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2023 15:47:18 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-natural/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We often come up with complicated and costly schemes to improve our lives (buy that new gadget, watch that new show everyone is talking about), when simpler zero-cost solutions may have better chances of actually having a positive impact. In another tiny post, I share a quick tip on how to enhance your lab/work-life by using natural spaces. &lt;em&gt;This idea will also be familiar to long-time &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/newsletter/&#34;&gt;newsletter subscribers&lt;/a&gt;, as it was an early &amp;ldquo;newsletter exclusive&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reviewing doctoral well-being research (study report)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/review-wellbeing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 12:23:40 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/review-wellbeing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Doctoral well-being is &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/tags/wellbeing/&#34;&gt;one of the central topics in this blog&lt;/a&gt; (indeed, it was the one that &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;started it all&lt;/a&gt;, more than three years ago). While I have tried to base my writings in the peer-reviewed research of this area, so far my reading of it has been rather unsystematic. How do doctoral well-being researchers summarize this body of knowledge? In this post, I distill from the findings of a systematic literature review on doctoral well-being, teasing out topics and factors that we already knew about from previous posts as well as novel ones that we can try to act upon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Facing addiction to social media in the PhD</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/social-media-addiction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 23:55:08 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/social-media-addiction/</guid>
      <description>Are you spending more time on social media than you would like? Is your use of Facebook, Twitter, Instagram, TikTok&amp;hellip; hampering progress on your doctoral research? You are not alone: many doctoral students report in our workshops that spending too much time scrolling compulsively on social media is one of their biggest productivity challenges. Building upon the insights about dopamine and addiction from our previous post, here I go over eight concrete steps we can take to break this compulsion and do more of the things we think are really important (like finishing that thesis).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Addiction and the PhD (book extract)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/addiction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Apr 2022 12:06:48 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/addiction/</guid>
      <description>Social media, porn, eating sugary things, shopping, alcohol, or spending our days anxiously reading the news&amp;hellip; Most of us have behaviors or substances we do compulsively, to the point that it damages our relationships and our ability to achieve important goals (including, of course, finishing our PhD thesis). Dopamine is at the heart of these addictions. In this post, I distill lessons learned from reading Anna Lembke&amp;rsquo;s book &amp;ldquo;Dopamine Nation&amp;rdquo;1 about how dopamine works, how to face our addictions, and do more of what we think is important.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab series</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 16:59:14 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-series/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this blog I have often covered the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/&#34;&gt;mental health&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;wellbeing problems&lt;/a&gt; that may come with doing a PhD, if we are not careful. In this series of posts I look at the flip side of that, diving into the research on &lt;em&gt;thriving&lt;/em&gt; at work, to find out which practices may help us be a little happier during our research, and how to diagnose ourselves about what aspects of our research activity can most be improved.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 5: Kindness</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2019 19:12:54 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Even if you feel that your research contributes to a bigger purpose, even if you work at it with great engagement, even if you&amp;rsquo;re resilient to setbacks and misfortune&amp;hellip; still your time working in research can suck. This week I look at the final missing piece in our search for a happier (research) workplace: the quality of our social interactions with others. Particularly, how positive connections and prosocial behaviors can help us &lt;em&gt;thrive&lt;/em&gt; at work (not just survive). In this post, I examine some of the main components of a prosocial workplace, how to assess them for yourself, and a few research-backed practices to make your lab a kinder place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 4: Resilience</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 19:58:29 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;No matter how meaningful your research feels to you, no matter how engaged you are when doing it, sometimes things just don&amp;rsquo;t work out as you expected. Papers get rejected, proposals are not funded, data gets mangled and needs to be collected again&amp;hellip; plus all the non-research-related stumbling blocks that life throws at us, from sickness to accidents or family tragedies. How fast and how well can we recover from those setbacks that throw us off balance? This fourth post in the series goes over the concept of resilience as an important pillar for staying happy and fulfilled while working in research. Read below for instruments you can use to gauge it, and practices to help you stay resilient in the face of difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 3: Engagement</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Sep 2019 19:10:43 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever found yourself avoiding your supervisor, or the thesis meetings, or just not wanting to open the manuscript file you have to finish? Then you might have some problems engaging with your research work. In this third post of the series on finding more happiness in your research, I look at how engagement at work is defined, how to assess your own levels of engagement, and some research-backed practices to help you engage better with your work and find your &amp;ldquo;flow&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 2: Purpose</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2019 09:45:01 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Continuing with last week&amp;rsquo;s post on &amp;ldquo;happiness at work&amp;rdquo;, in this post I explore the first of the four pillars for a happier workplace: the sense that your work has a &lt;em&gt;purpose&lt;/em&gt;, that it is personally meaningful to you. Read on to learn to self-assess your sense of purpose at work, and get some ideas on how to make your research work feel more meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 1: What is happiness?</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 16:43:50 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Being a Ph.D. student and being happy sometimes feel like two incompatible states. However, we all know someone that seems to enjoy greatly their work, even their &lt;em&gt;dissertation&lt;/em&gt; work (heck, I have to confess I&amp;rsquo;ve been one such annoying person myself sometimes). What things make people love their work? Apparently, an entire branch of positive psychology has been delving into this question for decades. This post is the first of a series that adapts insights and practices for greater &amp;ldquo;happiness at work&amp;rdquo; from a massive open online course (MOOC), to the work life of doctoral students (and academics more generally).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>