<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>http://ahappyphd.org/categories/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blog on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 May 2019 01:01:58 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ahappyphd.org/categories/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>On cultivating (and reining) curiosity</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/cultivate-curiosity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2019 01:01:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/cultivate-curiosity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One would think that research, as the pursuit of new knowledge, is mostly based upon curiosity. However, the daily grind of research life can erode that sense of excitement students have about delving into the unknown. In this post, I explore the role of curiosity in doctoral studies, and look at a few practices and tricks to keep the flame of curiosity alight (without burning the village!).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to deal with to-do list overwhelm</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/to-do-list-overwhelm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/to-do-list-overwhelm/</guid>
      <description>The to-do list is an essential staple of an organized, reliable doctoral student (or academic). Yet, have you ever looked at your task list and felt anxious, certain that you have too much to do and too little time? In this post, I review several routines that have helped me overcome this ubiquitous feeling.
I have been working (in the industry and in academia) for about twenty years now. Yet, periodically, I look at my to-do list, or at the list of “projects I’m doing”, and I feel my heart rate rise.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ask A Happy Ph.D. - Student edition</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/ask-happy-phd-student/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Apr 2019 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/ask-happy-phd-student/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This time I would like to turn the mike over to you, PhD students, and let &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; tell &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt; what you want to hear about in this blog (I will do a separate one for supervisors and supervision later on). What would you like to know about doing a Ph.D., or being a (happier, more productive) PhD student?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Choosing not to drop out: a view from self-determination theory</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/choosing-not-drop-out/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/choosing-not-drop-out/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/drop-out-phd/&#34;&gt;last week&amp;rsquo;s post&lt;/a&gt;, we established that dropping out of a Ph.D. (or thinking about it) is surprisingly common, and we saw demographic and socio-economic factors that seem related to doctoral attrition. In this post, I dive into another strand of research that relates doctoral dropout with a general theory of human motivation: &lt;em&gt;self-determination theory&lt;/em&gt;. This research helps explain why you may persist and finish your doctorate (and even have fun doing it), despite having such socio-economic factors playing against you. Or vice-versa. The post also gleans practical advice from the literature on doctoral attrition, in the hope of helping students and supervisors avoid this common pitfall.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who drops out of the Ph.D.?</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/drop-out-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/drop-out-phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Aside from the fact that doing a Ph.D. &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;seems to put you at a greater risk of being anxious or depressed&lt;/a&gt; than other occupations, some students may also face the question: will I ever finish my thesis &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;? This post digs into research about doctoral attrition and completion, and what factors seem to make dropping out more likely. Do not give up!&amp;hellip; unless you really want to.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Ten Commandments of scientific writing</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/10-commandments-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/10-commandments-writing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The writing of a paper (or the dissertation itself) is often a long process, along which many decisions are made: should I send my ideas for feedback now, or generate more polished text? should I think of the target journal now or decide once I have the finished draft? et cetera. To finish this mini-series of posts on writing (&lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/why-writing-is-hard/&#34;&gt;why writing papers is hard&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers/&#34;&gt;how I write papers&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers2/&#34;&gt;the second part of that writing process&lt;/a&gt;), I review here the main principles and lessons that I have learned after more than 10 years of writing scientific papers. I hope they help you navigate these decisions if you are in doubt, or if you have to step out of the usual writing process due to unexpected events.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I write papers (Part 2)</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2019 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Writing a paper is one of the hardest, but most creative parts of a Ph.D. Very often, we do not know where to start, what to do at what point, or when to get feedback from our collaborators. In &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers/&#34;&gt;a previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I started describing in detail the process I normally follow to write my scientific papers. This post explains the rest of the process, from the outlining until you send your manuscript off to the journal/conference. One would think that this is straightforward, just &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ejv2_CkZRHo&#34;&gt;scribbling and scribbling&lt;/a&gt;, right?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I write papers</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2019 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is plenty of advice out there on how to write academic publications, from general stylistic tips to field-specific guides. Yet, I&amp;rsquo;ve found most of that advice tends to be abstract, or focused on the final product, never giving you a step-by-step account of the process. In this post, I share the writing process I find myself using after 70+ academic publications. This will give you an idea of where to start writing your paper (especially if you have never written one), and it will show you that all polished papers have humble (even crappy) origins. Kill perfectionism, and the dreaded &amp;ldquo;academic writer&amp;rsquo;s block&amp;rdquo; will eventually disappear.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baking papers, or why scientific writing is so difficult</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/why-writing-is-hard/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/why-writing-is-hard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Writing (papers or the dissertation itself) is one of the activities that many doctoral students hate the most. Why is this act of communication so difficult for us? As a prelude to my post on &amp;ldquo;how I write papers&amp;rdquo;, I expose some misconceptions we seem to have about scientific writing and what are good ways to learn it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Risk factors for depression and anxiety in doing a Ph.D.</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a follow-up to &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;the first post in this blog&lt;/a&gt;, I dig a little deeper in some of the research on anxiety and depression during doctoral studies, to find &amp;ldquo;risk factors&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;correlates&amp;rdquo; that seem to often come along these depressive symptoms. I hope that the awareness of these factors (from gender to other things you can actually change in your everyday life) will help you understand why some people struggle doing a PhD, while for others it seems a piece of cake. Change what you do and put the odds on your side!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The second reason why I write this blog</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/second-reason/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/second-reason/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Initially, I thought that I was doing this to help the PhD students around me (and others like them elsewhere) to pass through the dissertation process more effectively, with less stress. But at some point, I realized that other, more selfish, reasons were playing out as well. In this personal account I reflect on a chronic problem of academics and Ph.D. students alike, and how I face it through this blog.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Productivity tip: the Pomodoro technique</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most basic, flexible and effective productivity techniques, which I&amp;rsquo;ve been using for many years.  I know many PhD students and academics that swear by it, but I am still surprised by others who do not know about it. In this post I come back to its origins, how to do it, and how I have combined it with other routines to keep me on track. Essential in this age of smartphones, social media and other constant distractions!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD tool: The CQOCE diagram</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/cqoce-diagram/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/cqoce-diagram/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By far, this is the tool (as in, &amp;ldquo;thinking tool&amp;rdquo;) which I recommend most often to PhD students. This diagram summarizes your main research questions, thesis contributions and evidence of their usefulness. While painful to make, this brutal synthesis exercise is also a powerful communication tool. In this post, I explain how it works, its origins, and how making 18+ versions of it helped me through my PhD. Copy the provided template and use it in your PhD supervision meetings or even in the PhD defense!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is doing a Ph.D. bad... for your mental wellbeing?</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 15:47:47 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a growing body of research that indicates that doing a doctoral dissertation can be taxing on the mental health of PhD students, with depression, anxiety, or burnout as potential pitfalls. Is this problem real and, if so, how bad is it? In this post, I review several recent studies, some of which also offer insights about potential risk factors. This also kickstarts the whole idea of this blog, as a way to increase awareness about these difficulties, and offer practical tips and tricks to survive such a difficult period.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>