<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Anxiety on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>http://ahappyphd.org/tags/anxiety/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Anxiety on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2020 11:50:55 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ahappyphd.org/tags/anxiety/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A Monday Mantra for times of coronavirus</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2020 11:50:55 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the spread of the COVID-19 pandemic, and increasing restrictions on movement and other aspects of life, also come anxiety, fear and a strange sense of unreality. Doing anything related to your PhD seems unusually hard, or pointless… even dangerous, compared with being continuously in the lookout for the latest news or advice on what to do. In this post, I share a &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-1/&#34;&gt;mantra&lt;/a&gt; and a few other tips that I use to help myself stay sane and (kinda) productive in these difficult times.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Risk factors for depression and anxiety in doing a Ph.D.</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a follow-up to &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;the first post in this blog&lt;/a&gt;, I dig a little deeper in some of the research on anxiety and depression during doctoral studies, to find &amp;ldquo;risk factors&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;correlates&amp;rdquo; that seem to often come along these depressive symptoms. I hope that the awareness of these factors (from gender to other things you can actually change in your everyday life) will help you understand why some people struggle doing a PhD, while for others it seems a piece of cake. Change what you do and put the odds on your side!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The second reason why I write this blog</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/second-reason/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/second-reason/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Initially, I thought that I was doing this to help the PhD students around me (and others like them elsewhere) to pass through the dissertation process more effectively, with less stress. But at some point, I realized that other, more selfish, reasons were playing out as well. In this personal account I reflect on a chronic problem of academics and Ph.D. students alike, and how I face it through this blog.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is doing a Ph.D. bad... for your mental wellbeing?</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 15:47:47 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a growing body of research that indicates that doing a doctoral dissertation can be taxing on the mental health of PhD students, with depression, anxiety, or burnout as potential pitfalls. Is this problem real and, if so, how bad is it? In this post, I review several recent studies, some of which also offer insights about potential risk factors. This also kickstarts the whole idea of this blog, as a way to increase awareness about these difficulties, and offer practical tips and tricks to survive such a difficult period.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>