<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Question on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/question/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Question on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 12:36:55 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/question/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A hiatus... and more BIG PhD questions</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/more-questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 12:36:55 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/more-questions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After a long hiatus for personal reasons, we are back in business! Continuing from &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/should-i-do/&#34;&gt;our last post from 2021&lt;/a&gt;, here I highlight one of the blog&amp;rsquo;s big foci for this starting year: the &amp;ldquo;big PhD questions&amp;rdquo;. The post goes over what Google has to say about this (!) and asks for your ideas and opinions on what big questions about the doctorate we should investigate next at the &amp;ldquo;A Happy PhD&amp;rdquo; blog.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Big PhD questions: Should I do a PhD?</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/should-i-do/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 15:21:05 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/should-i-do/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are reading this, chances are that you have already decided to do a PhD. Yet, you may know someone who is considering a doctoral degree (or you may be offering such a position as a supervisor to prospective students). This post is for &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt;. In this new type of post, we will look at big questions facing any PhD student. Today, we analyze the question that precedes all the other big PhD questions: &amp;ldquo;should I do a PhD?&amp;rdquo;. Below, I offer a couple of quick, simple ways to look at this important life decision, and a list of 10 factors to consider when offered (or seeking) a PhD position.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>