<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Deliberate on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/deliberate/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Deliberate on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 10:50:36 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/deliberate/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A PhD So Good It Can&#39;t Be Ignored (II) -- Mission, a System, and a Case Study (book extract)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/phd-so-good-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 10:50:36 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/phd-so-good-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have now established that &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/phd-so-good-1/&#34;&gt;a PhD provides plenty of opportunity&lt;/a&gt; to develop mastery and (in many cases) autonomy. Yet, these properties alone do not always ensure a remarkable and satisfying research career. In this second part of the book extract from Newport’s &lt;em&gt;So Good They Can’t Ignore You&lt;/em&gt;, we look at an additional piece in the puzzle—having a &amp;ldquo;mission&amp;rdquo;—and summarize the book’s system of practices to develop both mastery and mission, which can be applied directly during the PhD. I conclude with some critiques of the book and a case study to test whether these ideas map to my own research career thus far.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A PhD So Good It Can&#39;t Be Ignored -- Passion, Practice, and Control (book extract)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/phd-so-good-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 10:50:36 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/phd-so-good-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A doctorate is typically the first step in a longer (academic or otherwise) research career. Many think of it as a grueling rite of passage one must endure to get the job they want later on. But are there ways we can do the PhD to set us up for a remarkable and satisfying career? Are there ways we can make the PhD journey itself feel like a &amp;ldquo;good job&amp;rdquo;? In the first part of this book extract, we draw lessons from Cal Newport&amp;rsquo;s book &lt;em&gt;So Good They Can&amp;rsquo;t Ignore You&lt;/em&gt;, about &amp;ldquo;passion traps&amp;rdquo;, we look at properties of a good PhD job, focusing on mastery, control, and how to develop them for a more satisfying PhD (and beyond).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>