<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Supervision on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>http://ahappyphd.org/tags/supervision/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Supervision on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 16:49:59 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ahappyphd.org/tags/supervision/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Supervisor Quickie: the Post-It Feedback Method</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-feedback/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 16:49:59 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-feedback/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever spent hours providing feedback over a colleague&amp;rsquo;s (or a student&amp;rsquo;s) paper? And have you ever found afterwards that many of your carefully-crafted, thoughtful comments had been ignored? In this &amp;ldquo;quickie&amp;rdquo; post for supervisors (or for anyone giving internal feedback), I share a small trick that I use lately to avoid these situations&amp;hellip; and get better outcomes for everyone involved.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advising for progress: tips for PhD supervisors</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/advising-progress/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2020 09:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/advising-progress/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/&#34;&gt;a previous post&lt;/a&gt;, we have seen the crucial role that having a sense of progress plays, not only in the productivity, but also in the engagement and persistence of a PhD student towards the doctorate. While this recognition (and the practices to &amp;ldquo;make progress visible&amp;rdquo; we saw) put a big emphasis on the student as the main active agent, PhD students are not the only actors in this play. Is there anything that doctoral &lt;em&gt;supervisors&lt;/em&gt; can do to help? In this post, I go over some of the same management research on progress and our own evidence from the field, looking at what supervisors can do to support their students in perceiving continuous progress that eventually leads to a finished doctoral thesis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>