<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Values on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>http://ahappyphd.org/tags/values/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Values on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 15:21:05 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ahappyphd.org/tags/values/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Big PhD questions: Should I do a PhD?</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/should-i-do/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 15:21:05 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/should-i-do/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are reading this, chances are that you have already decided to do a PhD. Yet, you may know someone who is considering a doctoral degree (or you may be offering such a position as a supervisor to prospective students). This post is for &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt;. In this new type of post, we will look at big questions facing any PhD student. Today, we analyze the question that precedes all the other big PhD questions: &amp;ldquo;should I do a PhD?&amp;rdquo;. Below, I offer a couple of quick, simple ways to look at this important life decision, and a list of 10 factors to consider when offered (or seeking) a PhD position.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making important decisions about the doctorate (II)</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 11:59:28 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What can we do, when we have to take a hard decision about the PhD (like changing supervisors or leaving doctoral studies altogether) but we don&amp;rsquo;t really know which way to go? In the continuation to &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-1/&#34;&gt;last week&amp;rsquo;s post&lt;/a&gt;, we see how to go about the actual decision-making, to choose the option that has the best chances to satisfy us in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making important decisions about the doctorate (I)</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 18:59:31 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the PhD (and beyond), we sometimes face a difficult situation, and we have to take a hard decision: do I leave my PhD? do I take an unrelated job to earn more money while I try to finish the PhD? do I seek a new supervisor that better supports me? do I accept the change of direction that my supervisor is suggesting? In this two-part post series, I will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; give the answer to those hard questions, but rather provide a decision &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; that can help us find the option that is right &lt;em&gt;for us&lt;/em&gt;, in our particular circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to be a PhD student</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-to-be/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 09:33:48 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-to-be/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Not a few of the people that read this blog, do so with a very clear outcome in mind: to finish their PhD, to get that damned piece of paper saying that they’re doctors. In this struggle, we (yes, I did that too) often forget that the PhD is more of a &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; (a learning, a practice) than it is an outcome. In this adaptation of a poem by Wendell Berry, I take a stab at what it took for me to become a researcher. I write this as much for you as for myself – to remind myself that, in a sense, we never cease to be students, we remain always beginners in the new knowledge that we (and others) create with our research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 2: Purpose</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2019 09:45:01 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Continuing with last week&amp;rsquo;s post on &amp;ldquo;happiness at work&amp;rdquo;, in this post I explore the first of the four pillars for a happier workplace: the sense that your work has a &lt;em&gt;purpose&lt;/em&gt;, that it is personally meaningful to you. Read on to learn to self-assess your sense of purpose at work, and get some ideas on how to make your research work feel more meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>