<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thesis on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/thesis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Thesis on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 08:15:13 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/thesis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A happy Master thesis: Progress and appropriation even before the PhD</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happy-master/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 08:15:13 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happy-master/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Feelings of being stuck, of not knowing where we’re going, self-doubt, guilt… are not exclusive to the doctoral thesis journey. Despite their smaller scope, other long projects with little feedback or structure (like a master thesis) share the same motivational pitfalls and may induce the same kind of uncomfortable experience at times. In this two-part post series, we review key advice and simple practices which could also be useful to help us face these capstone projects.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swath and Dive: A pattern for PhD defense presentations</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/swath-dive/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 13:29:23 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/swath-dive/</guid>
      <description>In recent times I&amp;rsquo;m having the fortune of seeing several of my own doctoral students approach the end of the doctoral journey (yes, it does end!). As they submit the dissertation and prepare for their defense, there is one piece of advice I find myself giving again and again, about how to tackle the impossible task of presenting multiple years of research work in less than one hour. In this post, I describe a &amp;ldquo;presentation design pattern&amp;rdquo; for thesis defenses, which builds upon classic conceptualization exercises advocated in the blog.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Doctoral Consortium format for times of COVID</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/doctoral-consortium/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 09:35:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/doctoral-consortium/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Doctoral Consortia are events (often, at scientific conferences) where doctoral students present their dissertation ideas and get expert feedback on them. I have co-organized a few of these events during the first waves of the pandemic, which students seemed to find useful (the events, not the pandemic!). In this post, I describe the (online) event format that we followed, in case it helps future organizers of similar events. If you are a PhD student, I hope this post will also encourage you to attend one!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD tool: Map out your PhD</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/map-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 18:32:52 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/map-thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We know that &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/&#34;&gt;steady everyday progress&lt;/a&gt; is a crucial factor in finishing a PhD. In previous posts, we have seen &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/&#34;&gt;productivity&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/to-do-list-overwhelm/&#34;&gt;techniques&lt;/a&gt; to support us in taking more of these daily steps. Yet, a lot of walking does not necessarily get us anywhere. We need to know that we are actually getting past key reference points, closer to our final destination. In this post, I propose a diagramming exercise to map out key obstacles, milestones and the &amp;ldquo;everyday fuel&amp;rdquo; that propels us past them in our journey towards PhD completion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD tool: The CQOCE diagram</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/cqoce-diagram/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/cqoce-diagram/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By far, this is the tool (as in, &amp;ldquo;thinking tool&amp;rdquo;) which I recommend most often to PhD students. This diagram summarizes your main research questions, thesis contributions and evidence of their usefulness. While painful to make, this brutal synthesis exercise is also a powerful communication tool. In this post, I explain how it works, its origins, and how making 18+ versions of it helped me through my PhD. Copy the provided template and use it in your PhD supervision meetings or even in the PhD defense!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>