<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/authors/luis-p.-prieto/</link>
    <description>Recent content on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 12:10:57 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/authors/luis-p.-prieto/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tiny practice: Beating procrastination with The Right Now List</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-rightnow/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 12:10:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-rightnow/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the top &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/productivity-challenges/&#34;&gt;barriers to PhD productivity&lt;/a&gt; is procrastination. Have you ever found yourself with a big ugly task getting stale in your to-do list, repeatedly postponed because it is too big, too abstract, or makes you somehow uncomfortable? This tiny practice post gives you an simple trick to beat this sort of procrastination.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ChatGPT&#39;s doctoral productivity advice... and four ideas the algorithm will (probably) not give you</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chatgpt-productivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2023 10:21:11 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chatgpt-productivity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We know that &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/&#34;&gt;making progress&lt;/a&gt; is a critical motivational factor in finishing a PhD &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; maintaining good mental health while we do it. In turn, our &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/tags/productivity/&#34;&gt;productivity&lt;/a&gt; plays a big role in whether we make progress on our dissertation or not. As the first post in a series on doctoral productivity, I could not help but fall into one of the &lt;em&gt;thèmes du jour&lt;/em&gt;: whether ChatGPT and similar artificial intelligence (AI) tools can write a good piece about this topic. In this post, I go over a couple of iterations of (pretty good) computationally-generated advice, and finally give you a few ideas that I think are overlooked by the algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tiny idea: Use the Regret Test for daily decision-making</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-regret/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 10:33:53 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-regret/</guid>
      <description>Have you ever spent an hour scrolling on Instagram (or your ​social media addiction of choice​) and later realized with a pang of regret that such a time could have been spent much better doing something else you deeply ​value​? This sort of realization is at the core of this week&amp;rsquo;s blog post: a tiny practice to guide our daily decision making about what to do next. This idea will also be familiar to long-time newsletter subscribers, as it was an early “newsletter exclusive”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breathing through the PhD: Breathwork in the doctorate</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/breathing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2023 11:39:38 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/breathing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the doctorate (and in our later lives as researchers) we have to deal with a wide variety of situations and tasks, some stressful, some requiring focus or calmness. Going to therapy, doing &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/avoidance/&#34;&gt;therapy-inspired reflection exercises&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/tags/journaling/&#34;&gt;journaling&lt;/a&gt;, and other practices are all very useful, but they require us to step &lt;em&gt;away&lt;/em&gt; from the difficult situation. If only there was a simple, free, portable tool to help us in such situations, something we could do in any occasion and which is evidence-based&amp;hellip; Wait, there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;! This post is about &lt;strong&gt;breathwork&lt;/strong&gt;, an array of tools with an increasing body of scientific evidence demonstrating its effectiveness. The post describes how we should breathe for better health and cognitive performance, and how different kinds of breathing patterns can help us cope with common challenging situations throughout the PhD.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tiny practice: Boost your workday happiness with natural spaces</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-natural/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2023 15:47:18 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-natural/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We often come up with complicated and costly schemes to improve our lives (buy that new gadget, watch that new show everyone is talking about), when simpler zero-cost solutions may have better chances of actually having a positive impact. In another tiny post, I share a quick tip on how to enhance your lab/work-life by using natural spaces. &lt;em&gt;This idea will also be familiar to long-time &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/newsletter/&#34;&gt;newsletter subscribers&lt;/a&gt;, as it was an early &amp;ldquo;newsletter exclusive&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tiny idea: Subtraction</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-subtraction/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2023 07:06:42 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-subtraction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In our efforts to fix our life&amp;rsquo;s problems, we often keep adding stuff to our lives and ideas to our theses, ignoring there&amp;rsquo;s an alternative. In another tiny post, I quickly share how you can harness the power of subtraction. &lt;em&gt;This idea will be familiar to long-time &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/newsletter/&#34;&gt;newsletter subscribers&lt;/a&gt;, as it was an early &amp;ldquo;newsletter exclusive&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tiny practice: Granny&#39;s rule</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-granny/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2023 07:25:41 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-granny/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We all tend to delay difficult, uncertain or scary tasks unnecessarily&amp;hellip; especially, those related to our thesis. How to avoid such procrastination? In this new kind of short post (so far only available to &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/newsletter/&#34;&gt;our newsletter subscribers&lt;/a&gt;), I share tiny practices or ideas that have had an outsized effect on my thinking or my research practice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A happy Master thesis: Progress and appropriation even before the PhD</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happy-master/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 08:15:13 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happy-master/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Feelings of being stuck, of not knowing where we’re going, self-doubt, guilt… are not exclusive to the doctoral thesis journey. Despite their smaller scope, other long projects with little feedback or structure (like a master thesis) share the same motivational pitfalls and may induce the same kind of uncomfortable experience at times. In this two-part post series, we review key advice and simple practices which could also be useful to help us face these capstone projects. But these can also be very useful if you are a PhD student just starting out!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intervision: Unblocking yourself... with a little help from some friends</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/intervision/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2022 16:45:22 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/intervision/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a PhD (and as doctoral supervisors) we often face situations where we feel blocked, with no idea of how to get out  or what to do next. In this post, the first of a series distilling wisdom from the latest round of &amp;ldquo;A Happy PhD&amp;rdquo; workshops, we look at a peer advice technique we have repeatedly use in the workshops to help students (and supervisors!) unblock. All you need is&amp;hellip; a little help from a small group of people.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Swath and Dive: A pattern for PhD defense presentations</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/swath-dive/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 13:29:23 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/swath-dive/</guid>
      <description>In recent times I&amp;rsquo;m having the fortune of seeing several of my own doctoral students approach the end of the doctoral journey (yes, it does end!). As they submit the dissertation and prepare for their defense, there is one piece of advice I find myself giving again and again, about how to tackle the impossible task of presenting multiple years of research work in less than one hour. In this post, I describe a &amp;ldquo;presentation design pattern&amp;rdquo; for thesis defenses, which builds upon classic conceptualization exercises advocated in the blog.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reviewing doctoral well-being research (study report)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/review-wellbeing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 12:23:40 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/review-wellbeing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Doctoral well-being is &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/tags/wellbeing/&#34;&gt;one of the central topics in this blog&lt;/a&gt; (indeed, it was the one that &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;started it all&lt;/a&gt;, more than three years ago). While I have tried to base my writings in the peer-reviewed research of this area, so far my reading of it has been rather unsystematic. How do doctoral well-being researchers summarize this body of knowledge? In this post, I distill from the findings of a systematic literature review on doctoral well-being, teasing out topics and factors that we already knew about from previous posts as well as novel ones that we can try to act upon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quickie: Preloading productive meditation (book extract)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/preloading/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 08:42:03 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/preloading/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have established that &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/scheduling-strategies/&#34;&gt;finding long periods of time&lt;/a&gt; for deep, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/create-consume/&#34;&gt;creative&lt;/a&gt; research tasks (be it writing a paper or designing our next study) is critical to achieve our thesis &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/map-thesis/&#34;&gt;milestones&lt;/a&gt; and finish the PhD. Yet, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/execution/&#34;&gt;we are all very busy&lt;/a&gt; and have limited time for such creativity. To help in solving this conundrum, this short post describes a technique I&amp;rsquo;ve been using lately to squeeze a few extra hours a week to make headway in those hard, creative research tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The four disciplines of executing your PhD (book extract)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/execution/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 10:11:55 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/execution/</guid>
      <description>Very often, the myriad of obligations, additional tasks, jobs and activities in our daily lives block us from making progress in our most important goals (like finishing that doctoral thesis!). This is especially true of part-time doctoral students that have a day job to make ends meet, but even full-time students face this challenge. Our behavior needs to change, but we can&amp;rsquo;t find what to change (or the energy to do it).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Four scheduling strategies of successful PhD students (book extract)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/scheduling-strategies/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2022 23:51:25 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/scheduling-strategies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ability to concentrate and do focused, cognitively-demanding work is crucial to finishing a PhD (and doing research in general). Yet, we often spend our days in emails, meetings and other busywork that does not bring us closer to completing our goal (e.g., the thesis!). How to keep the busyness at bay so that we dedicate more time to the important stuff? In this post, the first of a series based on Cal Newport&amp;rsquo;s classic book &lt;em&gt;Deep Work&lt;/em&gt;, we look at the high-level shape of a deep-worker&amp;rsquo;s calendar. What are the strategies that doctoral students have successfully used to find time to advance in producing their thesis materials?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting into the weeds of writing</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/weeds-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2022 01:14:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/weeds-writing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you feel like the prose of your papers is burdensome and rambling, even after lots of &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers/&#34;&gt;outlining and feedback&lt;/a&gt;? Do you often get feedback from co-authors about it being ambiguous, aimless or vague? Do you keep making the same writing mistakes again and again? The final step in drafting a paper (generating final prose &lt;em&gt;and editing it&lt;/em&gt; sentence-by-sentence for clarity) is laborious and often overlooked. In this short post, I point you to a set of proofreading/editing tips from another blog, and share with you one tip to help you detect those pesky errors and make your prose more punchy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Avoiding avoidance and other mental self-sabotage in the PhD</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/avoidance/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2022 11:17:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/avoidance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Does the thesis bring you a sense of anxiety, fear or discomfort? As we saw &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/am-i-normal/&#34;&gt;in a previous post&lt;/a&gt;, that is not an uncommon experience at certain points during the PhD. At the heart of many of our unsuccessful strategies to deal with these symptoms (including distraction and &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/addiction/&#34;&gt;addiction&lt;/a&gt;) is the notion of avoidance. In this post, we&amp;rsquo;ll explain what avoidance is, its key role in many mental health afflictions, and suggest exercises and strategies to help us overcome these challenges.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Create/Consume Hypothesis: A simple rule for more effective and valuable PhD work</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/create-consume/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2022 12:02:15 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/create-consume/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you start your workday full of energy and eager to tackle your research but find yourself by mid-morning already spent and demoralized? Does this happen after a flurry of email interactions, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/social-media-addiction/&#34;&gt;social media scrolling&lt;/a&gt;, or passive meetings? You may be experiencing the differential effects of creative and consumptive work on your motivation and energy. This post will go over a (still half-baked) idea about how different kinds of work energize us, and simple rules that we can implement for a more sustained sense of &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/&#34;&gt;progress&lt;/a&gt; and satisfaction with our (PhD or otherwise) work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Facing addiction to social media in the PhD</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/social-media-addiction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 23:55:08 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/social-media-addiction/</guid>
      <description>Are you spending more time on social media than you would like? Is your use of Facebook, Twitter, Instagram, TikTok&amp;hellip; hampering progress on your doctoral research? You are not alone: many doctoral students report in our workshops that spending too much time scrolling compulsively on social media is one of their biggest productivity challenges. Building upon the insights about dopamine and addiction from our previous post, here I go over eight concrete steps we can take to break this compulsion and do more of the things we think are really important (like finishing that thesis).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Addiction and the PhD (book extract)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/addiction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Apr 2022 12:06:48 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/addiction/</guid>
      <description>Social media, porn, eating sugary things, shopping, alcohol, or spending our days anxiously reading the news&amp;hellip; Most of us have behaviors or substances we do compulsively, to the point that it damages our relationships and our ability to achieve important goals (including, of course, finishing our PhD thesis). Dopamine is at the heart of these addictions. In this post, I distill lessons learned from reading Anna Lembke&amp;rsquo;s book &amp;ldquo;Dopamine Nation&amp;rdquo;1 about how dopamine works, how to face our addictions, and do more of what we think is important.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forget New Year&#39;s resolutions -- Do a Yearly Review instead</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/yearly-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jan 2022 12:13:04 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/yearly-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are like most of us, by now (end of February) your New Year&amp;rsquo;s resolutions will have fallen by the wayside. In recent years, I have stopped doing resolutions altogether. This post is about what I do now instead, heeding the advice of productivity systems and psychotherapy approaches: &lt;strong&gt;a yearly review&lt;/strong&gt;. This post goes over my particular yearly review process, and how it can give your research motivation (and satisfaction with life) a yearly boost.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A hiatus... and more BIG PhD questions</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/more-questions/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Jan 2022 12:36:55 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/more-questions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After a long hiatus for personal reasons, we are back in business! Continuing from &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/should-i-do/&#34;&gt;our last post from 2021&lt;/a&gt;, here I highlight one of the blog&amp;rsquo;s big foci for this starting year: the &amp;ldquo;big PhD questions&amp;rdquo;. The post goes over what Google has to say about this (!) and asks for your ideas and opinions on what big questions about the doctorate we should investigate next at the &amp;ldquo;A Happy PhD&amp;rdquo; blog.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Big PhD questions: Should I do a PhD?</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/should-i-do/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Oct 2021 15:21:05 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/should-i-do/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are reading this, chances are that you have already decided to do a PhD. Yet, you may know someone who is considering a doctoral degree (or you may be offering such a position as a supervisor to prospective students). This post is for &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt;. In this new type of post, we will look at big questions facing any PhD student. Today, we analyze the question that precedes all the other big PhD questions: &amp;ldquo;should I do a PhD?&amp;rdquo;. Below, I offer a couple of quick, simple ways to look at this important life decision, and a list of 10 factors to consider when offered (or seeking) a PhD position.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quickie: How many PhD students are anxious or depressed (or will drop out) worldwide?</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-many-phd-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Sep 2021 13:44:49 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-many-phd-students/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the catalysts that kickstarted this blog was the realization that &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;PhD students are at a higher risk of mental health problems&lt;/a&gt; than other students and professionals. Yet, how bad is the problem really? Exactly how many PhD students are &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/am-i-normal/&#34;&gt;suffering&lt;/a&gt; from depression or severe anxiety &lt;em&gt;right now&lt;/em&gt;? How many will &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/drop-out-phd/&#34;&gt;drop out&lt;/a&gt;? In this quickie post, I pull from the data of a few recent studies to give a concrete, numeric &lt;del&gt;answer&lt;/del&gt; guesstimate to these questions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chronobiology addendum: A neurobiologist&#39;s guide to a healthy and productive day</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chronobiology-addendum/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 18:14:20 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chronobiology-addendum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In previous posts, we have seen &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chronobiology/&#34;&gt;how chronotype can influence our productivity&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chrono-breaks/&#34;&gt;how we can tweak our breaks&lt;/a&gt; to make the most of the ebbs and flows of our daily energy. But, how exactly can we use this chronobiology knowledge to craft a daily routine that is both productive and healthy, and fitting to our particular situation? In this post, I borrow from the habits and routines of an expert on the topic (Stanford neurobiologist Andrew Huberman) ten easy protocols you can put in practice to make every day your best day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Journaling for the doctorate (II): How to journal effectively</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/journaling-tips/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 12:45:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/journaling-tips/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Journaling during your doctorate can have a &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/journaling-benefits/&#34;&gt;host of benefits&lt;/a&gt; (for self-knowledge, mental and physical health). However, not everyone will benefit to the same degree, and different kinds of journaling have different advantages&amp;hellip; if done correctly over a sustained period of time. In this post, I will go over different research-backed journaling exercises and tips to make your journaling most effective.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Journaling for the doctorate (I): Types and benefits</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/journaling-benefits/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Aug 2021 10:40:54 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/journaling-benefits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you ever get the feeling, at the end of the day, that you have achieved nothing? or that days and weeks pass by, indistinguishable from one another, time slipping away like water between your fingers? Is your mind an unfocused maelstrom of swirling thoughts, ruminating again and again about the same worrying (or plain silly) things? Journaling has been proposed (both by ancient philosophers and modern researchers) as having many benefits, from dealing with stress and trauma, to just understanding ourselves a little better. But, can journaling be useful for us in facing the challenges of a PhD? In this post, I will take a look at the research on different kinds of journaling and what are their effects for mental and physical health.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quickie: A simple trick to get better answers to your open questions</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-answers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 09:34:01 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-answers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During a PhD (or any research) we need to answer not only the research questions we have set for ourselves, but also a host of other questions. Many of them are reflective and/or open in nature. Yet, we often slap whatever answer first pops into our brains, and run with it. In today&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;quickie&amp;rdquo; post, I share a simple practice that can help in getting over this &lt;a href=&#34;https://fs.blog/2021/06/availability-bias-cognitive-distortion/&#34;&gt;availability bias&lt;/a&gt; to get deeper, better answers to your open reflective questions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Doctoral Consortium format for times of COVID</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/doctoral-consortium/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 09:35:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/doctoral-consortium/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Doctoral Consortia are events (often, at scientific conferences) where doctoral students present their dissertation ideas and get expert feedback on them. I have co-organized a few of these events during the first waves of the pandemic, which students seemed to find useful (the events, not the pandemic!). In this post, I describe the (online) event format that we followed, in case it helps future organizers of similar events. If you are a PhD student, I hope this post will also encourage you to attend one!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on chronobiology for the PhD (II): The science of breaks</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chrono-breaks/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 May 2021 08:42:19 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chrono-breaks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Being the &amp;ldquo;cognitive athletes&amp;rdquo; they are, PhD students (and researchers) should take &lt;em&gt;rest&lt;/em&gt; very seriously, to perform at their best. Yet, not all breaks are created equal: timing and other factors affect their effectiveness. Continuing previous dives into &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chronobiology/&#34;&gt;chronobiology&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/holidays/&#34;&gt;taking holidays&lt;/a&gt;, this post goes over evidence-based tips and tricks to make your breaks the most restorative and energizing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Supporting different types of students to complete their PhD (Study report)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/supporting-types-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 08:50:08 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/supporting-types-phd/</guid>
      <description>Aside from PhD students&amp;rsquo; own motivational factors (e.g., how much progress they perceive, or how exhausted they are), the support they receive from supervisors is another key aspect related to doctoral completion. In the continuation of last week&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;study report&amp;rdquo;, we discuss how different kinds of supervisor support relate to those motivational factors and, eventually, the finishing of the doctorate. We will also see how supervisors could foster these motivational aspects and help their students complete the PhD.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What kind of doctoral student are you? Motivational profiles and completing the PhD (Study report)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/what-kind-phd-student/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 10:33:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/what-kind-phd-student/</guid>
      <description>Many factors seem to play out into whether we complete our PhD, or drop out of it. Some of them are external and largely uncontrollable (like financial or family problems), while others relate to our thesis project and motivation. In this new type of blog post (the &amp;ldquo;study report&amp;rdquo;), I dive into the results of a recent research study that defines five types of doctoral students, in terms of their motivational profile.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Monday Mantra to face uncomfortable emotions (#2 productivity challenge sneak peek)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/mantra-emotions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 08:26:34 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/mantra-emotions/</guid>
      <description>In a previous post, I mentioned that uncomfortable emotions (like guilt, anxiety or indecision) are one of the most common obstacles to productivity that our PhD students report. In preparation for a longer series of posts on &amp;ldquo;emotional first aid for the PhD&amp;rdquo;, I have found a short mental exercise that has helped me face those difficult emotions lately. Here it is, in the form of a card-based &amp;ldquo;Monday Mantra&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defusing task conflict in the PhD</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/task-conflict/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 09:38:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/task-conflict/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As we saw &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/productivity-challenges/&#34;&gt;in a recent post&lt;/a&gt;, “task conflict” is a common productivity challenge of doctoral students. As PhD students, we often have to juggle different identities, priorities, jobs, projects… along with doing the thesis itself. Yet, so often, it is the thesis-related tasks that keep getting pushed back. In this post, I will go over tips, practices and techniques that might be useful if you find yourself struggling with this particular challenge in your PhD.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The three most common productivity challenges of PhD students</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/productivity-challenges/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 19:52:14 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/productivity-challenges/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you ever feel, during your PhD, that you are not “productive enough”? Guess what, you are not alone. In this post, I share the three most frequently-appearing productivity problems voiced in doctoral workshops we have run in Estonia and Spain. I hope this shows PhD students that they are not alone&amp;hellip; and gives PhD supervisors hints about the hurdles their students often face (whether they mention them explicitly or not). Also, I will give a couple of simple rules to know if these are a problem for you particularly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD tool: Map out your PhD</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/map-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 18:32:52 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/map-thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We know that &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/&#34;&gt;steady everyday progress&lt;/a&gt; is a crucial factor in finishing a PhD. In previous posts, we have seen &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/&#34;&gt;productivity&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/to-do-list-overwhelm/&#34;&gt;techniques&lt;/a&gt; to support us in taking more of these daily steps. Yet, a lot of walking does not necessarily get us anywhere. We need to know that we are actually getting past key reference points, closer to our final destination. In this post, I propose a diagramming exercise to map out key obstacles, milestones and the &amp;ldquo;everyday fuel&amp;rdquo; that propels us past them in our journey towards PhD completion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Micro-breaks and two Monday Mantras to supercharge them</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/micro-break-mantras/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2020 16:29:18 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/micro-break-mantras/</guid>
      <description>When we are writing a research paper, we need to find long stretches of focused time to get that writing done. Yet, even if we find them, can we really sustain intense focus during two or more hours? Today&amp;rsquo;s post looks at a research-backed and often overlooked tool in our productivity toolbox: the micro-break. To top it up, I provide two &amp;ldquo;monday mantras&amp;rdquo; to make your micro-breaks even more effective.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on chronobiology for the PhD (I): Circadian rhythms</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chronobiology/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 13:56:27 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chronobiology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt, after lunch, that your mind cannot focus? or that, later on, writing suddenly feels effortless? If you have noticed trends in &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; these experiences happen, you have stumbled into the importance of chronobiology for your productivity. In this and following posts, I provide advice on how to organize your research work, based on chronobiology research. Today, circadian rhythms &amp;ndash; i.e., &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; to do &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; during the day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing exercise: sitting with uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/writing-uncertainty/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2020 16:57:21 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/writing-uncertainty/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever had this feeling, while writing, that your prose is leading nowhere? that right now it would be a great moment to defreeze the fridge? to check your phone, because someone may have texted? In this post, I offer a simple exercise to use next time these internal interruptions assail you during writing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Supervisor Quickie: the Post-It Feedback Method</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-feedback/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 16:49:59 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-feedback/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever spent hours providing feedback over a colleague&amp;rsquo;s (or a student&amp;rsquo;s) paper? And have you ever found afterwards that many of your carefully-crafted, thoughtful comments had been ignored? In this &amp;ldquo;quickie&amp;rdquo; post for supervisors (or for anyone giving internal feedback), I share a small trick that I use lately to avoid these situations&amp;hellip; and get better outcomes for everyone involved.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Latest News from A Happy PhD</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/news-october-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 17:24:44 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/news-october-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Just a quick update about what&amp;rsquo;s been going on lately at the &amp;lsquo;A Happy PhD&amp;rsquo; headquarters. Expect a change of pace in the next weeks: shorter, more regular posts, our new &amp;lsquo;Twitter Tuesdays&amp;rsquo;, and much more!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More effective group decision-making meetings</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/meeting-pattern/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 23:26:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/meeting-pattern/</guid>
      <description>Have you ever gone out of a supposedly important meeting, after more than one hour of talking, but still feeling like a poor (or obvious) decision has been made? In this post, I go over a simple pattern to organize more effective meetings when a group decision or proposal has to be made. Don&amp;rsquo;t be fooled by its simplicity: it&amp;rsquo;s much more effective than &amp;ldquo;business as usual&amp;rdquo; meetings, but people (including ourselves) will resist it fiercely, because it feels unnatural to act against our internalized meeting routines.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making important decisions about the doctorate (II)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 11:59:28 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What can we do, when we have to take a hard decision about the PhD (like changing supervisors or leaving doctoral studies altogether) but we don&amp;rsquo;t really know which way to go? In the continuation to &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-1/&#34;&gt;last week&amp;rsquo;s post&lt;/a&gt;, we see how to go about the actual decision-making, to choose the option that has the best chances to satisfy us in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making important decisions about the doctorate (I)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 18:59:31 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the PhD (and beyond), we sometimes face a difficult situation, and we have to take a hard decision: do I leave my PhD? do I take an unrelated job to earn more money while I try to finish the PhD? do I seek a new supervisor that better supports me? do I accept the change of direction that my supervisor is suggesting? In this two-part post series, I will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; give the answer to those hard questions, but rather provide a decision &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; that can help us find the option that is right &lt;em&gt;for us&lt;/em&gt;, in our particular circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Take your holidays… the right way</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/holidays/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 12:01:52 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/holidays/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a PhD student, one sometimes gets the impression that holidays are something that happens only to other people, or that one does not deserve them (I’m so behind on so many things!). Yet, what does the research say about taking holidays, is it really good for you as a doctoral student? Are there better or worse ways of taking a vacation? As preparation for the blog’s own summer hiatus, this post goes over the benefits, pitfalls, and optimal dynamics of taking a longer break.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Monday Mantra duo: The best advice about research that an artist never gave me</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 22:33:36 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-6/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We tend to think of research as rational, mechanistic, sterile, orderly. However, there are many things about research that are random, chaotic, and require loads of creativity (&lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/writing-papers-series/&#34;&gt;writing papers&lt;/a&gt; being only one example among many). Thus, it sometimes makes sense to think about research as an art… and sometimes we can reuse tricks and advice from the arts, to make better science. In this brief post, I give you a couple of those, from a well-known artist and writer, in the form of two &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-1/&#34;&gt;Monday Mantras&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Navigating authorship: a condensed crash course in setting authors for your paper</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/authorship/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2020 11:28:31 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/authorship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Defining who are the authors of your scientific papers, while apparently trivial, is sometimes a surprisingly difficult decision (especially, the first times we do it). As novice researchers, we may operate under conjectures or assumptions about how scientific authorship works, which may not necessarily be true. In this post, I go over several factors that often weigh in into that decision, and I provide a couple of tips and resources about how I would go about taking that decision, ideally.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Am I normal? An intro to mental health in the doctorate</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/am-i-normal/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 09:04:40 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/am-i-normal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By now, we have established that PhD students (and academics in general) &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;seem to be at a higher risk to develop mental health problems&lt;/a&gt; like depression or chronic stress. But, how can we know if &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; have one of these mental health problems, right here, right now? In this post, co-authored with colleague, friend and therapist Paula Odriozola-González, we go over a few basic concepts of psychopathology, and propose criteria and simple practices to help separate internal experiences that we all go through at one time or another, from the more serious stuff.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to be a PhD student</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-to-be/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Apr 2020 09:33:48 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-to-be/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Not a few of the people that read this blog, do so with a very clear outcome in mind: to finish their PhD, to get that damned piece of paper saying that they’re doctors. In this struggle, we (yes, I did that too) often forget that the PhD is more of a &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; (a learning, a practice) than it is an outcome. In this adaptation of a poem by Wendell Berry, I take a stab at what it took for me to become a researcher. I write this as much for you as for myself – to remind myself that, in a sense, we never cease to be students, we remain always beginners in the new knowledge that we (and others) create with our research.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quickie: How to be more mindful</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-mindfulness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 14:11:06 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-mindfulness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As our time at home increases due to quarantines and lockdowns, so does our opportunity to endlessly gossip, procrastinate or bitch about the global situation, our leaders and celebrities, or the people we happen to live with. Or, we could choose to be productive. We could choose to develop a new skill. Being mindful allows us to notice, in a non-judgmental way, the richness of life in and around us (yes, even when you’re locked down at home day after day). In this new kind of post (the “quickie”), I give you in brief a few reasons to develop such mindfulness, and three ways to start learning that skill, &lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Monday Mantra for times of coronavirus</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Mar 2020 11:50:55 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the spread of the COVID-19 pandemic, and increasing restrictions on movement and other aspects of life, also come anxiety, fear and a strange sense of unreality. Doing anything related to your PhD seems unusually hard, or pointless… even dangerous, compared with being continuously in the lookout for the latest news or advice on what to do. In this post, I share a &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-1/&#34;&gt;mantra&lt;/a&gt; and a few other tips that I use to help myself stay sane and (kinda) productive in these difficult times.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I revise my journal papers</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/revising/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2020 13:12:31 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/revising/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Along with &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/writing-papers-series/&#34;&gt;writing your first journal paper&lt;/a&gt;, doing a substantial revision to your manuscript upon receiving the reviewers’ comments is one often-cited painful moment of any doctoral process. This complex act of scientific communication involves balancing diplomacy with integrity, creativity and systematicity. In this post, I go over the concrete (and, sometimes, counter-intuitive) steps I follow to revise my journal papers upon receiving peer-review critiques, as well as some basic principles to increase your chances of success and avoid unnecessary suffering.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Sleep</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/on-sleep/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2020 20:34:26 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/on-sleep/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Is your PhD giving you beautiful dreams or horrible nightmares? In either case, you probably should be getting more of them. Sleep (or, rather, lack of sleep) is one of the best-known and most consistent &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/&#34;&gt;risk factors related to depression, anxiety&lt;/a&gt;, and host of other mental and physical health issues. It is also one of the factors (mostly) under our control &amp;ndash; even if it often gets the back seat with respect to other priorities like work, social life, family, or the latest season of our favorite TV show. In this post, I review some of the (very extense, and rather terrifying) research about the effects that lack of sleep has on humans in general, and PhD students in particular. The post also points you to practices and resources to help you in sleeping not only longer, but also better. Keep your delicate mind and body machinery in optimal working condition!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advising for progress: tips for PhD supervisors</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/advising-progress/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2020 09:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/advising-progress/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/&#34;&gt;a previous post&lt;/a&gt;, we have seen the crucial role that having a sense of progress plays, not only in the productivity, but also in the engagement and persistence of a PhD student towards the doctorate. While this recognition (and the practices to &amp;ldquo;make progress visible&amp;rdquo; we saw) put a big emphasis on the student as the main active agent, PhD students are not the only actors in this play. Is there anything that doctoral &lt;em&gt;supervisors&lt;/em&gt; can do to help? In this post, I go over some of the same management research on progress and our own evidence from the field, looking at what supervisors can do to support their students in perceiving continuous progress that eventually leads to a finished doctoral thesis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultivating the progress loop in your PhD</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 11:30:48 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt like you are &amp;ldquo;stuck&amp;rdquo; in your PhD, making no progress, or going in circles? If so, you are in good company &amp;ndash; most PhD students report such experience at one time or another during their doctoral process. The normalcy of this experience, however, should not make us dismiss it as unimportant. In this post I review research that speaks to the importance of this sense of progress (or the lack of it) to our engagement with work and the eventual completion (or dropping out) of the PhD. The post also reviews several everyday practices to cultivate your own sense of progress.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One year of &#39;A Happy PhD&#39;: What happened in 2019</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/ahappyphd-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2020 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/ahappyphd-2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Wow, does time fly by! During the Christmas and New Year&amp;rsquo;s hiatus, I had the chance to pause and review what has happened with the blog since I started it about one year ago. Read on if you want to know which were the most popular posts of 2019, where does this blog&amp;rsquo;s readership come from, and what lies in waiting for 2020&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday Mantra #4: On attention</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2019 10:49:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ability to pay attention is one of the most important assets of a PhD student (or researcher) and plays a crucial role on our focus and productivity, but also on our creativity and wellbeing. In this month&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-1/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Monday Mantra&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, I give you not one, but &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; sentences that you can use to remind yourself to manage this resource wisely. Choose your favorite!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report from the trenches: of calendar tricks and time scarcity</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/calendar-trick/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 17:41:51 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/calendar-trick/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/to-do-list-overwhelm/&#34;&gt;a previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I proposed the use of your favorite calendar app to store all your TO-DOs and avoid over-committing. I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying this productivity trick on myself for the past few months. In this new kind of blog post, I report on the results of this self-experiment, and the effect it has had on my own productivity and wellbeing. I also provide some practical tips and tricks, in case you want to try it out for yourself. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Too_long;_didn%27t_read&#34;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/a&gt;: It works&amp;hellip; if you are a bit careful.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Productivity tip: How I do weekly reviews</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/weekly-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2019 12:54:50 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/weekly-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Despite the emphasis I have made so far in developing productive and healthy everyday routines (from &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/to-do-list-overwhelm/&#34;&gt;to-do lists&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/&#34;&gt;pomodoros&lt;/a&gt;), not everything about productivity happens at this tactical, day-to-day level. In this short post, I guide you through what I think is the centerpiece of my own personal productivity system: the weekly review.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday mantra #3: When you have too many open fronts</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 17:01:51 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt that you have too many threads open in your research work, and you cannot seem to make substantial progress in any of them? You are not alone. After closing the long series of posts on &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-series/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;happiness in the lab&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, a bit of a lighter read this week. In this post I give very short advice that you can use as a &amp;ldquo;mantra&amp;rdquo; for this and the coming weeks, somewhat related to staying productive &amp;ndash; but with a twist.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab series</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 16:59:14 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-series/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this blog I have often covered the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/&#34;&gt;mental health&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;wellbeing problems&lt;/a&gt; that may come with doing a PhD, if we are not careful. In this series of posts I look at the flip side of that, diving into the research on &lt;em&gt;thriving&lt;/em&gt; at work, to find out which practices may help us be a little happier during our research, and how to diagnose ourselves about what aspects of our research activity can most be improved.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing research papers series</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/writing-papers-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 16:59:00 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/writing-papers-series/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Writing research papers is one of the most dreaded (and most unavoidable) activities for many people during the PhD. In this series of posts I explore some of the reasons why writing research papers is difficult when one arrives at the PhD, and explain what concrete writing process I find myself following after more than a decade of academic writing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 5: Kindness</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2019 19:12:54 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Even if you feel that your research contributes to a bigger purpose, even if you work at it with great engagement, even if you&amp;rsquo;re resilient to setbacks and misfortune&amp;hellip; still your time working in research can suck. This week I look at the final missing piece in our search for a happier (research) workplace: the quality of our social interactions with others. Particularly, how positive connections and prosocial behaviors can help us &lt;em&gt;thrive&lt;/em&gt; at work (not just survive). In this post, I examine some of the main components of a prosocial workplace, how to assess them for yourself, and a few research-backed practices to make your lab a kinder place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 4: Resilience</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 19:58:29 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;No matter how meaningful your research feels to you, no matter how engaged you are when doing it, sometimes things just don&amp;rsquo;t work out as you expected. Papers get rejected, proposals are not funded, data gets mangled and needs to be collected again&amp;hellip; plus all the non-research-related stumbling blocks that life throws at us, from sickness to accidents or family tragedies. How fast and how well can we recover from those setbacks that throw us off balance? This fourth post in the series goes over the concept of resilience as an important pillar for staying happy and fulfilled while working in research. Read below for instruments you can use to gauge it, and practices to help you stay resilient in the face of difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 3: Engagement</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Sep 2019 19:10:43 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever found yourself avoiding your supervisor, or the thesis meetings, or just not wanting to open the manuscript file you have to finish? Then you might have some problems engaging with your research work. In this third post of the series on finding more happiness in your research, I look at how engagement at work is defined, how to assess your own levels of engagement, and some research-backed practices to help you engage better with your work and find your &amp;ldquo;flow&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 2: Purpose</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2019 09:45:01 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Continuing with last week&amp;rsquo;s post on &amp;ldquo;happiness at work&amp;rdquo;, in this post I explore the first of the four pillars for a happier workplace: the sense that your work has a &lt;em&gt;purpose&lt;/em&gt;, that it is personally meaningful to you. Read on to learn to self-assess your sense of purpose at work, and get some ideas on how to make your research work feel more meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 1: What is happiness?</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 16:43:50 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Being a Ph.D. student and being happy sometimes feel like two incompatible states. However, we all know someone that seems to enjoy greatly their work, even their &lt;em&gt;dissertation&lt;/em&gt; work (heck, I have to confess I&amp;rsquo;ve been one such annoying person myself sometimes). What things make people love their work? Apparently, an entire branch of positive psychology has been delving into this question for decades. This post is the first of a series that adapts insights and practices for greater &amp;ldquo;happiness at work&amp;rdquo; from a massive open online course (MOOC), to the work life of doctoral students (and academics more generally).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday Mantra: On scientific communication and research in general</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2019 19:35:02 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When we present our research to others, in a conference or in writing, we often feel insecure: is what I found obvious? is there a fatal flaw in my reasoning or my data analysis? will the audience finally &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impostor_syndrome&#34;&gt;unmask me as the impostor I am&lt;/a&gt;? This week&amp;rsquo;s short &amp;ldquo;Monday Mantra&amp;rdquo; goes at the heart of such unproductive self-talk. What is all this really about?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tips for attending scientific conferences</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/going-to-conferences/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2019 18:03:07 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/going-to-conferences/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Going to an international conference, to present your own work or to better understand a scientific community, is usually an intense (even stressful) experience. As a doctoral student, probably even more so. In this post I share a selection of advice and tricks to make your next conference more pleasant (and useful in the long-term). Go forth, and enjoy a few days of &amp;ldquo;geeking out&amp;rdquo; with fellow researchers!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A small hiatus, and a Monday Mantra</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2019 21:28:44 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A shorter post this week, to warn you about a small hiatus in the blog (due to taking a &amp;ldquo;disconnected break&amp;rdquo;), and to propose a new post format: Monday Mantras. As the first exercise in this format, I propose you use the best shortest productivity advice I&amp;rsquo;ve ever read.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD tool: Pitching your research with the NABC model</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/pitching-nabc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2019 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/pitching-nabc/</guid>
      <description>As a Ph.D. student, you very often have to present what your research is about. Maybe you want to get quick feedback from a visiting professor. Or you need to give a talk at a conference or doctoral consortium. In this post, I go over a technique adapted from a large US research lab I once visited. I will walk you through its simple four- (or five-)part structure, including real examples from my own work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On cultivating (and reining) curiosity</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/cultivate-curiosity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2019 01:01:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/cultivate-curiosity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One would think that research, as the pursuit of new knowledge, is mostly based upon curiosity. However, the daily grind of research life can erode that sense of excitement students have about delving into the unknown. In this post, I explore the role of curiosity in doctoral studies, and look at a few practices and tricks to keep the flame of curiosity alight (without burning the village!).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to deal with to-do list overwhelm</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/to-do-list-overwhelm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/to-do-list-overwhelm/</guid>
      <description>The to-do list is an essential staple of an organized, reliable doctoral student (or academic). Yet, have you ever looked at your task list and felt anxious, certain that you have too much to do and too little time? In this post, I review several routines that have helped me overcome this ubiquitous feeling.
I have been working (in the industry and in academia) for about twenty years now. Yet, periodically, I look at my to-do list, or at the list of “projects I’m doing”, and I feel my heart rate rise.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ask A Happy Ph.D. - Student edition</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/ask-happy-phd-student/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Apr 2019 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/ask-happy-phd-student/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This time I would like to turn the mike over to you, PhD students, and let &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; tell &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt; what you want to hear about in this blog (I will do a separate one for supervisors and supervision later on). What would you like to know about doing a Ph.D., or being a (happier, more productive) PhD student?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Choosing not to drop out: a view from self-determination theory</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/choosing-not-drop-out/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/choosing-not-drop-out/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/drop-out-phd/&#34;&gt;last week&amp;rsquo;s post&lt;/a&gt;, we established that dropping out of a Ph.D. (or thinking about it) is surprisingly common, and we saw demographic and socio-economic factors that seem related to doctoral attrition. In this post, I dive into another strand of research that relates doctoral dropout with a general theory of human motivation: &lt;em&gt;self-determination theory&lt;/em&gt;. This research helps explain why you may persist and finish your doctorate (and even have fun doing it), despite having such socio-economic factors playing against you. Or vice-versa. The post also gleans practical advice from the literature on doctoral attrition, in the hope of helping students and supervisors avoid this common pitfall.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who drops out of the Ph.D.?</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/drop-out-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/drop-out-phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Aside from the fact that doing a Ph.D. &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;seems to put you at a greater risk of being anxious or depressed&lt;/a&gt; than other occupations, some students may also face the question: will I ever finish my thesis &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;? This post digs into research about doctoral attrition and completion, and what factors seem to make dropping out more likely. Do not give up!&amp;hellip; unless you really want to.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Ten Commandments of scientific writing</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/10-commandments-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/10-commandments-writing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The writing of a paper (or the dissertation itself) is often a long process, along which many decisions are made: should I send my ideas for feedback now, or generate more polished text? should I think of the target journal now or decide once I have the finished draft? et cetera. To finish this mini-series of posts on writing (&lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/why-writing-is-hard/&#34;&gt;why writing papers is hard&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers/&#34;&gt;how I write papers&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers2/&#34;&gt;the second part of that writing process&lt;/a&gt;), I review here the main principles and lessons that I have learned after more than 10 years of writing scientific papers. I hope they help you navigate these decisions if you are in doubt, or if you have to step out of the usual writing process due to unexpected events.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I write papers (Part 2)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2019 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Writing a paper is one of the hardest, but most creative parts of a Ph.D. Very often, we do not know where to start, what to do at what point, or when to get feedback from our collaborators. In &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers/&#34;&gt;a previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I started describing in detail the process I normally follow to write my scientific papers. This post explains the rest of the process, from the outlining until you send your manuscript off to the journal/conference. One would think that this is straightforward, just &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ejv2_CkZRHo&#34;&gt;scribbling and scribbling&lt;/a&gt;, right?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I write papers</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2019 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is plenty of advice out there on how to write academic publications, from general stylistic tips to field-specific guides. Yet, I&amp;rsquo;ve found most of that advice tends to be abstract, or focused on the final product, never giving you a step-by-step account of the process. In this post, I share the writing process I find myself using after 70+ academic publications. This will give you an idea of where to start writing your paper (especially if you have never written one), and it will show you that all polished papers have humble (even crappy) origins. Kill perfectionism, and the dreaded &amp;ldquo;academic writer&amp;rsquo;s block&amp;rdquo; will eventually disappear.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baking papers, or why scientific writing is so difficult</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/why-writing-is-hard/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/why-writing-is-hard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Writing (papers or the dissertation itself) is one of the activities that many doctoral students hate the most. Why is this act of communication so difficult for us? As a prelude to my post on &amp;ldquo;how I write papers&amp;rdquo;, I expose some misconceptions we seem to have about scientific writing and what are good ways to learn it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Risk factors for depression and anxiety in doing a Ph.D.</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a follow-up to &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;the first post in this blog&lt;/a&gt;, I dig a little deeper in some of the research on anxiety and depression during doctoral studies, to find &amp;ldquo;risk factors&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;correlates&amp;rdquo; that seem to often come along these depressive symptoms. I hope that the awareness of these factors (from gender to other things you can actually change in your everyday life) will help you understand why some people struggle doing a PhD, while for others it seems a piece of cake. Change what you do and put the odds on your side!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The second reason why I write this blog</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/second-reason/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/second-reason/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Initially, I thought that I was doing this to help the PhD students around me (and others like them elsewhere) to pass through the dissertation process more effectively, with less stress. But at some point, I realized that other, more selfish, reasons were playing out as well. In this personal account I reflect on a chronic problem of academics and Ph.D. students alike, and how I face it through this blog.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Productivity tip: the Pomodoro technique</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most basic, flexible and effective productivity techniques, which I&amp;rsquo;ve been using for many years.  I know many PhD students and academics that swear by it, but I am still surprised by others who do not know about it. In this post I come back to its origins, how to do it, and how I have combined it with other routines to keep me on track. Essential in this age of smartphones, social media and other constant distractions!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD tool: The CQOCE diagram</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/cqoce-diagram/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/cqoce-diagram/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By far, this is the tool (as in, &amp;ldquo;thinking tool&amp;rdquo;) which I recommend most often to PhD students. This diagram summarizes your main research questions, thesis contributions and evidence of their usefulness. While painful to make, this brutal synthesis exercise is also a powerful communication tool. In this post, I explain how it works, its origins, and how making 18+ versions of it helped me through my PhD. Copy the provided template and use it in your PhD supervision meetings or even in the PhD defense!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is doing a Ph.D. bad... for your mental wellbeing?</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 15:47:47 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a growing body of research that indicates that doing a doctoral dissertation can be taxing on the mental health of PhD students, with depression, anxiety, or burnout as potential pitfalls. Is this problem real and, if so, how bad is it? In this post, I review several recent studies, some of which also offer insights about potential risk factors. This also kickstarts the whole idea of this blog, as a way to increase awareness about these difficulties, and offer practical tips and tricks to survive such a difficult period.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>