<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Group on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/group/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Group on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2022 16:45:22 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/group/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Intervision: Unblocking yourself... with a little help from some friends</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/intervision/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2022 16:45:22 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/intervision/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In a PhD (and as doctoral supervisors) we often face situations where we feel blocked, with no idea of how to get out  or what to do next. In this post, the first of a series distilling wisdom from the latest round of &amp;ldquo;A Happy PhD&amp;rdquo; workshops, we look at a peer advice technique we have repeatedly use in the workshops to help students (and supervisors!) unblock. All you need is&amp;hellip; a little help from a small group of people.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More effective group decision-making meetings</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/meeting-pattern/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 23:26:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/meeting-pattern/</guid>
      <description>Have you ever gone out of a supposedly important meeting, after more than one hour of talking, but still feeling like a poor (or obvious) decision has been made? In this post, I go over a simple pattern to organize more effective meetings when a group decision or proposal has to be made. Don&amp;rsquo;t be fooled by its simplicity: it&amp;rsquo;s much more effective than &amp;ldquo;business as usual&amp;rdquo; meetings, but people (including ourselves) will resist it fiercely, because it feels unnatural to act against our internalized meeting routines.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>