<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Quickie on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/quickie/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Quickie on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 09:34:01 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/quickie/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Quickie: A simple trick to get better answers to your open questions</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-answers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 09:34:01 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-answers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During a PhD (or any research) we need to answer not only the research questions we have set for ourselves, but also a host of other questions. Many of them are reflective and/or open in nature. Yet, we often slap whatever answer first pops into our brains, and run with it. In today&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;quickie&amp;rdquo; post, I share a simple practice that can help in getting over this &lt;a href=&#34;https://fs.blog/2021/06/availability-bias-cognitive-distortion/&#34;&gt;availability bias&lt;/a&gt; to get deeper, better answers to your open reflective questions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Supervisor Quickie: the Post-It Feedback Method</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-feedback/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 16:49:59 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-feedback/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever spent hours providing feedback over a colleague&amp;rsquo;s (or a student&amp;rsquo;s) paper? And have you ever found afterwards that many of your carefully-crafted, thoughtful comments had been ignored? In this &amp;ldquo;quickie&amp;rdquo; post for supervisors (or for anyone giving internal feedback), I share a small trick that I use lately to avoid these situations&amp;hellip; and get better outcomes for everyone involved.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quickie: How to be more mindful</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-mindfulness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 14:11:06 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-mindfulness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As our time at home increases due to quarantines and lockdowns, so does our opportunity to endlessly gossip, procrastinate or bitch about the global situation, our leaders and celebrities, or the people we happen to live with. Or, we could choose to be productive. We could choose to develop a new skill. Being mindful allows us to notice, in a non-judgmental way, the richness of life in and around us (yes, even when you’re locked down at home day after day). In this new kind of post (the “quickie”), I give you in brief a few reasons to develop such mindfulness, and three ways to start learning that skill, &lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>