<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Conference on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/conference/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Conference on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 09:35:04 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/conference/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A Doctoral Consortium format for times of COVID</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/doctoral-consortium/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 09:35:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/doctoral-consortium/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Doctoral Consortia are events (often, at scientific conferences) where doctoral students present their dissertation ideas and get expert feedback on them. I have co-organized a few of these events during the first waves of the pandemic, which students seemed to find useful (the events, not the pandemic!). In this post, I describe the (online) event format that we followed, in case it helps future organizers of similar events. If you are a PhD student, I hope this post will also encourage you to attend one!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tips for attending scientific conferences</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/going-to-conferences/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2019 18:03:07 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/going-to-conferences/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Going to an international conference, to present your own work or to better understand a scientific community, is usually an intense (even stressful) experience. As a doctoral student, probably even more so. In this post I share a selection of advice and tricks to make your next conference more pleasant (and useful in the long-term). Go forth, and enjoy a few days of &amp;ldquo;geeking out&amp;rdquo; with fellow researchers!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD tool: Pitching your research with the NABC model</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/pitching-nabc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2019 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/pitching-nabc/</guid>
      <description>As a Ph.D. student, you very often have to present what your research is about. Maybe you want to get quick feedback from a visiting professor. Or you need to give a talk at a conference or doctoral consortium. In this post, I go over a technique adapted from a large US research lab I once visited. I will walk you through its simple four- (or five-)part structure, including real examples from my own work.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>