<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Focus on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/focus/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Focus on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 08:42:03 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/focus/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Quickie: Preloading productive meditation (book extract)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/preloading/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 08:42:03 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/preloading/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have established that &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/scheduling-strategies/&#34;&gt;finding long periods of time&lt;/a&gt; for deep, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/create-consume/&#34;&gt;creative&lt;/a&gt; research tasks (be it writing a paper or designing our next study) is critical to achieve our thesis &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/map-thesis/&#34;&gt;milestones&lt;/a&gt; and finish the PhD. Yet, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/execution/&#34;&gt;we are all very busy&lt;/a&gt; and have limited time for such creativity. To help in solving this conundrum, this short post describes a technique I&amp;rsquo;ve been using lately to squeeze a few extra hours a week to make headway in those hard, creative research tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The four disciplines of executing your PhD (book extract)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/execution/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 10:11:55 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/execution/</guid>
      <description>Very often, the myriad of obligations, additional tasks, jobs and activities in our daily lives block us from making progress in our most important goals (like finishing that doctoral thesis!). This is especially true of part-time doctoral students that have a day job to make ends meet, but even full-time students face this challenge. Our behavior needs to change, but we can&amp;rsquo;t find what to change (or the energy to do it).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Four scheduling strategies of successful PhD students (book extract)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/scheduling-strategies/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2022 23:51:25 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/scheduling-strategies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ability to concentrate and do focused, cognitively-demanding work is crucial to finishing a PhD (and doing research in general). Yet, we often spend our days in emails, meetings and other busywork that does not bring us closer to completing our goal (e.g., the thesis!). How to keep the busyness at bay so that we dedicate more time to the important stuff? In this post, the first of a series based on Cal Newport&amp;rsquo;s classic book &lt;em&gt;Deep Work&lt;/em&gt;, we look at the high-level shape of a deep-worker&amp;rsquo;s calendar. What are the strategies that doctoral students have successfully used to find time to advance in producing their thesis materials?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chronobiology addendum: A neurobiologist&#39;s guide to a healthy and productive day</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chronobiology-addendum/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 18:14:20 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chronobiology-addendum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In previous posts, we have seen &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chronobiology/&#34;&gt;how chronotype can influence our productivity&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chrono-breaks/&#34;&gt;how we can tweak our breaks&lt;/a&gt; to make the most of the ebbs and flows of our daily energy. But, how exactly can we use this chronobiology knowledge to craft a daily routine that is both productive and healthy, and fitting to our particular situation? In this post, I borrow from the habits and routines of an expert on the topic (Stanford neurobiologist Andrew Huberman) ten easy protocols you can put in practice to make every day your best day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on chronobiology for the PhD (II): The science of breaks</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chrono-breaks/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 May 2021 08:42:19 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chrono-breaks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Being the &amp;ldquo;cognitive athletes&amp;rdquo; they are, PhD students (and researchers) should take &lt;em&gt;rest&lt;/em&gt; very seriously, to perform at their best. Yet, not all breaks are created equal: timing and other factors affect their effectiveness. Continuing previous dives into &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chronobiology/&#34;&gt;chronobiology&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/holidays/&#34;&gt;taking holidays&lt;/a&gt;, this post goes over evidence-based tips and tricks to make your breaks the most restorative and energizing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defusing task conflict in the PhD</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/task-conflict/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 09:38:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/task-conflict/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As we saw &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/productivity-challenges/&#34;&gt;in a recent post&lt;/a&gt;, “task conflict” is a common productivity challenge of doctoral students. As PhD students, we often have to juggle different identities, priorities, jobs, projects… along with doing the thesis itself. Yet, so often, it is the thesis-related tasks that keep getting pushed back. In this post, I will go over tips, practices and techniques that might be useful if you find yourself struggling with this particular challenge in your PhD.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The three most common productivity challenges of PhD students</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/productivity-challenges/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 19:52:14 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/productivity-challenges/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you ever feel, during your PhD, that you are not “productive enough”? Guess what, you are not alone. In this post, I share the three most frequently-appearing productivity problems voiced in doctoral workshops we have run in Estonia and Spain. I hope this shows PhD students that they are not alone&amp;hellip; and gives PhD supervisors hints about the hurdles their students often face (whether they mention them explicitly or not). Also, I will give a couple of simple rules to know if these are a problem for you particularly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Micro-breaks and two Monday Mantras to supercharge them</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/micro-break-mantras/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Dec 2020 16:29:18 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/micro-break-mantras/</guid>
      <description>When we are writing a research paper, we need to find long stretches of focused time to get that writing done. Yet, even if we find them, can we really sustain intense focus during two or more hours? Today&amp;rsquo;s post looks at a research-backed and often overlooked tool in our productivity toolbox: the micro-break. To top it up, I provide two &amp;ldquo;monday mantras&amp;rdquo; to make your micro-breaks even more effective.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on chronobiology for the PhD (I): Circadian rhythms</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chronobiology/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2020 13:56:27 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chronobiology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt, after lunch, that your mind cannot focus? or that, later on, writing suddenly feels effortless? If you have noticed trends in &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; these experiences happen, you have stumbled into the importance of chronobiology for your productivity. In this and following posts, I provide advice on how to organize your research work, based on chronobiology research. Today, circadian rhythms &amp;ndash; i.e., &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; to do &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; during the day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing exercise: sitting with uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/writing-uncertainty/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2020 16:57:21 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/writing-uncertainty/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever had this feeling, while writing, that your prose is leading nowhere? that right now it would be a great moment to defreeze the fridge? to check your phone, because someone may have texted? In this post, I offer a simple exercise to use next time these internal interruptions assail you during writing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday mantra #3: When you have too many open fronts</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 17:01:51 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt that you have too many threads open in your research work, and you cannot seem to make substantial progress in any of them? You are not alone. After closing the long series of posts on &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-series/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;happiness in the lab&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, a bit of a lighter read this week. In this post I give very short advice that you can use as a &amp;ldquo;mantra&amp;rdquo; for this and the coming weeks, somewhat related to staying productive &amp;ndash; but with a twist.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Productivity tip: the Pomodoro technique</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most basic, flexible and effective productivity techniques, which I&amp;rsquo;ve been using for many years.  I know many PhD students and academics that swear by it, but I am still surprised by others who do not know about it. In this post I come back to its origins, how to do it, and how I have combined it with other routines to keep me on track. Essential in this age of smartphones, social media and other constant distractions!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>