<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Principles on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/principles/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Principles on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2020 13:12:31 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/principles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How I revise my journal papers</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/revising/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2020 13:12:31 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/revising/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Along with &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/writing-papers-series/&#34;&gt;writing your first journal paper&lt;/a&gt;, doing a substantial revision to your manuscript upon receiving the reviewers’ comments is one often-cited painful moment of any doctoral process. This complex act of scientific communication involves balancing diplomacy with integrity, creativity and systematicity. In this post, I go over the concrete (and, sometimes, counter-intuitive) steps I follow to revise my journal papers upon receiving peer-review critiques, as well as some basic principles to increase your chances of success and avoid unnecessary suffering.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Ten Commandments of scientific writing</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/10-commandments-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/10-commandments-writing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The writing of a paper (or the dissertation itself) is often a long process, along which many decisions are made: should I send my ideas for feedback now, or generate more polished text? should I think of the target journal now or decide once I have the finished draft? et cetera. To finish this mini-series of posts on writing (&lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/why-writing-is-hard/&#34;&gt;why writing papers is hard&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers/&#34;&gt;how I write papers&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers2/&#34;&gt;the second part of that writing process&lt;/a&gt;), I review here the main principles and lessons that I have learned after more than 10 years of writing scientific papers. I hope they help you navigate these decisions if you are in doubt, or if you have to step out of the usual writing process due to unexpected events.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>