<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pattern on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/pattern/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pattern on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 13:29:23 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/pattern/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Swath and Dive: A pattern for PhD defense presentations</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/swath-dive/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2022 13:29:23 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/swath-dive/</guid>
      <description>In recent times I&amp;rsquo;m having the fortune of seeing several of my own doctoral students approach the end of the doctoral journey (yes, it does end!). As they submit the dissertation and prepare for their defense, there is one piece of advice I find myself giving again and again, about how to tackle the impossible task of presenting multiple years of research work in less than one hour. In this post, I describe a &amp;ldquo;presentation design pattern&amp;rdquo; for thesis defenses, which builds upon classic conceptualization exercises advocated in the blog.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quickie: A simple trick to get better answers to your open questions</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-answers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 09:34:01 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-answers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During a PhD (or any research) we need to answer not only the research questions we have set for ourselves, but also a host of other questions. Many of them are reflective and/or open in nature. Yet, we often slap whatever answer first pops into our brains, and run with it. In today&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;quickie&amp;rdquo; post, I share a simple practice that can help in getting over this &lt;a href=&#34;https://fs.blog/2021/06/availability-bias-cognitive-distortion/&#34;&gt;availability bias&lt;/a&gt; to get deeper, better answers to your open reflective questions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Supervisor Quickie: the Post-It Feedback Method</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-feedback/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 16:49:59 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-feedback/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever spent hours providing feedback over a colleague&amp;rsquo;s (or a student&amp;rsquo;s) paper? And have you ever found afterwards that many of your carefully-crafted, thoughtful comments had been ignored? In this &amp;ldquo;quickie&amp;rdquo; post for supervisors (or for anyone giving internal feedback), I share a small trick that I use lately to avoid these situations&amp;hellip; and get better outcomes for everyone involved.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More effective group decision-making meetings</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/meeting-pattern/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 23:26:49 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/meeting-pattern/</guid>
      <description>Have you ever gone out of a supposedly important meeting, after more than one hour of talking, but still feeling like a poor (or obvious) decision has been made? In this post, I go over a simple pattern to organize more effective meetings when a group decision or proposal has to be made. Don&amp;rsquo;t be fooled by its simplicity: it&amp;rsquo;s much more effective than &amp;ldquo;business as usual&amp;rdquo; meetings, but people (including ourselves) will resist it fiercely, because it feels unnatural to act against our internalized meeting routines.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>