<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Deep work on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/deep-work/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Deep work on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 08:42:03 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/deep-work/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Quickie: Preloading productive meditation (book extract)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/preloading/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 08:42:03 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/preloading/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have established that &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/scheduling-strategies/&#34;&gt;finding long periods of time&lt;/a&gt; for deep, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/create-consume/&#34;&gt;creative&lt;/a&gt; research tasks (be it writing a paper or designing our next study) is critical to achieve our thesis &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/map-thesis/&#34;&gt;milestones&lt;/a&gt; and finish the PhD. Yet, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/execution/&#34;&gt;we are all very busy&lt;/a&gt; and have limited time for such creativity. To help in solving this conundrum, this short post describes a technique I&amp;rsquo;ve been using lately to squeeze a few extra hours a week to make headway in those hard, creative research tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Four scheduling strategies of successful PhD students (book extract)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/scheduling-strategies/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2022 23:51:25 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/scheduling-strategies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ability to concentrate and do focused, cognitively-demanding work is crucial to finishing a PhD (and doing research in general). Yet, we often spend our days in emails, meetings and other busywork that does not bring us closer to completing our goal (e.g., the thesis!). How to keep the busyness at bay so that we dedicate more time to the important stuff? In this post, the first of a series based on Cal Newport&amp;rsquo;s classic book &lt;em&gt;Deep Work&lt;/em&gt;, we look at the high-level shape of a deep-worker&amp;rsquo;s calendar. What are the strategies that doctoral students have successfully used to find time to advance in producing their thesis materials?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>