<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Competence on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/competence/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Competence on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 08:50:08 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/competence/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Supporting different types of students to complete their PhD (Study report)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/supporting-types-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 08:50:08 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/supporting-types-phd/</guid>
      <description>Aside from PhD students&amp;rsquo; own motivational factors (e.g., how much progress they perceive, or how exhausted they are), the support they receive from supervisors is another key aspect related to doctoral completion. In the continuation of last week&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;study report&amp;rdquo;, we discuss how different kinds of supervisor support relate to those motivational factors and, eventually, the finishing of the doctorate. We will also see how supervisors could foster these motivational aspects and help their students complete the PhD.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What kind of doctoral student are you? Motivational profiles and completing the PhD (Study report)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/what-kind-phd-student/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 10:33:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/what-kind-phd-student/</guid>
      <description>Many factors seem to play out into whether we complete our PhD, or drop out of it. Some of them are external and largely uncontrollable (like financial or family problems), while others relate to our thesis project and motivation. In this new type of blog post (the &amp;ldquo;study report&amp;rdquo;), I dive into the results of a recent research study that defines five types of doctoral students, in terms of their motivational profile.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>