<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Negative thoughts on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>http://ahappyphd.org/tags/negative-thoughts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Negative thoughts on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 08:26:34 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ahappyphd.org/tags/negative-thoughts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A Monday Mantra to face uncomfortable emotions (#2 productivity challenge sneak peek)</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/mantra-emotions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 08:26:34 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/mantra-emotions/</guid>
      <description>In a previous post, I mentioned that uncomfortable emotions (like guilt, anxiety or indecision) are one of the most common obstacles to productivity that our PhD students report. In preparation for a longer series of posts on &amp;ldquo;emotional first aid for the PhD&amp;rdquo;, I have found a short mental exercise that has helped me face those difficult emotions lately. Here it is, in the form of a card-based &amp;ldquo;Monday Mantra&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Am I normal? An intro to mental health in the doctorate</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/am-i-normal/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 09:04:40 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/am-i-normal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By now, we have established that PhD students (and academics in general) &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;seem to be at a higher risk to develop mental health problems&lt;/a&gt; like depression or chronic stress. But, how can we know if &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; have one of these mental health problems, right here, right now? In this post, co-authored with colleague, friend and therapist Paula Odriozola-González, we go over a few basic concepts of psychopathology, and propose criteria and simple practices to help separate internal experiences that we all go through at one time or another, from the more serious stuff.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>