<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Procrastination on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/procrastination/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Procrastination on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 17:12:17 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/procrastination/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How to restart our PhD habit after a productivity slump</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/restart-phd-habit/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 17:12:17 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/restart-phd-habit/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A family member dies, or their health fails catastrophically, requiring intense caregiving. A workload spike at our thesis-unrelated job becomes  an ongoing plateau. Life&amp;rsquo;s logistics somehow magically align to get in the way, again and again. The experience of a &amp;ldquo;hair on fire&amp;rdquo; emergency morphing into a prolonged thesis progress slump is more common than we think. My recent hiatus from blogging has helped me see this common problem of doctoral students in a new light (and to experience it firsthand). This post explores mindsets and strategies that can help us return to making &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/&#34;&gt;regular progress&lt;/a&gt; on our non-urgent but important projects (a.k.a. the thesis).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tiny practice: Beating procrastination with The Right Now List</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-rightnow/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2024 12:10:57 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-rightnow/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the top &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/productivity-challenges/&#34;&gt;barriers to PhD productivity&lt;/a&gt; is procrastination. Have you ever found yourself with a big ugly task getting stale in your to-do list, repeatedly postponed because it is too big, too abstract, or makes you somehow uncomfortable? This tiny practice post gives you an simple trick to beat this sort of procrastination.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tiny practice: Granny&#39;s rule</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-granny/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2023 07:25:41 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-granny/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We all tend to delay difficult, uncertain or scary tasks unnecessarily&amp;hellip; especially, those related to our thesis. How to avoid such procrastination? In this new kind of short post (so far only available to &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/newsletter/&#34;&gt;our newsletter subscribers&lt;/a&gt;), I share tiny practices or ideas that have had an outsized effect on my thinking or my research practice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>