<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dropout on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>http://ahappyphd.org/tags/dropout/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dropout on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 12:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ahappyphd.org/tags/dropout/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Choosing not to drop out: a view from self-determination theory</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/choosing-not-drop-out/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/choosing-not-drop-out/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/drop-out-phd/&#34;&gt;last week&#39;s post&lt;/a&gt;, we established that dropping out of a Ph.D. (or thinking about it) is surprisingly common, and we saw demographic and socio-economic factors that seem related to doctoral attrition. In this post, I dive into another strand of research that relates doctoral dropout with a general theory of human motivation: &lt;em&gt;self-determination theory&lt;/em&gt;. This research helps explain why you may persist and finish your doctorate (and even have fun doing it), despite having such socio-economic factors playing against you. Or vice-versa. The post also gleans practical advice from the literature on doctoral attrition, in the hope of helping students and supervisors avoid this common pitfall.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who drops out of the Ph.D.?</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/drop-out-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/drop-out-phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Aside from the fact that doing a Ph.D. &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;seems to put you at a greater risk of being anxious or depressed&lt;/a&gt; than other occupations, some students may also face the question: will I ever finish my thesis &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;? This post digs into research about doctoral attrition and completion, and what factors seem to make dropping out more likely. Do not give up!&amp;hellip; unless you really want to.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>