<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Book extract on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/book-extract/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Book extract on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2022 23:51:25 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/book-extract/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Four scheduling strategies of successful PhD students (book extract)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/scheduling-strategies/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2022 23:51:25 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/scheduling-strategies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ability to concentrate and do focused, cognitively-demanding work is crucial to finishing a PhD (and doing research in general). Yet, we often spend our days in emails, meetings and other busywork that does not bring us closer to completing our goal (e.g., the thesis!). How to keep the busyness at bay so that we dedicate more time to the important stuff? In this post, the first of a series based on Cal Newport&amp;rsquo;s classic book &lt;em&gt;Deep Work&lt;/em&gt;, we look at the high-level shape of a deep-worker&amp;rsquo;s calendar. What are the strategies that doctoral students have successfully used to find time to advance in producing their thesis materials?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Addiction and the PhD (book extract)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/addiction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Apr 2022 12:06:48 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/addiction/</guid>
      <description>Social media, porn, eating sugary things, shopping, alcohol, or spending our days anxiously reading the news&amp;hellip; Most of us have behaviors or substances we do compulsively, to the point that it damages our relationships and our ability to achieve important goals (including, of course, finishing our PhD thesis). Dopamine is at the heart of these addictions. In this post, I distill lessons learned from reading Anna Lembke&amp;rsquo;s book &amp;ldquo;Dopamine Nation&amp;rdquo;1 about how dopamine works, how to face our addictions, and do more of what we think is important.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>