<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Practice on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/practice/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Practice on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2024 10:13:12 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/practice/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tiny idea: To-do lists are menus</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-menus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2024 10:13:12 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-menus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Overwhelmed by your endless to-do list? Stressed because of the many PhD-related tasks you need to &amp;ldquo;go through&amp;rdquo;? As &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/to-do-list-overwhelm/&#34;&gt;we discussed previously in the blog&lt;/a&gt;, you are not alone (and ask any already-doctors whether this feeling goes away after graduation). Lately, as I struggle with not-so-new-parenthood-unproductivity in my own research, I have been reminded several times of a mental reframe I first encountered in productivity writer &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.oliverburkeman.com/&#34;&gt;Oliver Burkeman&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s work. This simple metaphor helped me change my relationship with my to-do list, without hurting my productivity (more probably, the opposite).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tiny practice: Boost your workday happiness with natural spaces</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-natural/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Oct 2023 15:47:18 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-natural/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We often come up with complicated and costly schemes to improve our lives (buy that new gadget, watch that new show everyone is talking about), when simpler zero-cost solutions may have better chances of actually having a positive impact. In another tiny post, I share a quick tip on how to enhance your lab/work-life by using natural spaces. &lt;em&gt;This idea will also be familiar to long-time &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/newsletter/&#34;&gt;newsletter subscribers&lt;/a&gt;, as it was an early &amp;ldquo;newsletter exclusive&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tiny practice: Granny&#39;s rule</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-granny/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2023 07:25:41 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/tiny-granny/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We all tend to delay difficult, uncertain or scary tasks unnecessarily&amp;hellip; especially, those related to our thesis. How to avoid such procrastination? In this new kind of short post (so far only available to &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/newsletter/&#34;&gt;our newsletter subscribers&lt;/a&gt;), I share tiny practices or ideas that have had an outsized effect on my thinking or my research practice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>