<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2019 09:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ahappyphd.org/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How I write papers</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2019 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-i-write-papers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is plenty of advice out there on how to write academic publications, from general stylistic tips to field-specific guides. Yet, I&amp;rsquo;ve found most of that advice tends to be abstract, or focused on the final product, never giving you a step-by-step account of the process. In this post, I share the writing process I find myself using after 70+ academic publications. This will give you an idea of where to start writing your paper (especially if you have never written one), and it will show you that all polished papers have humble (even crappy) origins. Kill perfectionism, and the dreaded &amp;ldquo;academic writer&amp;rsquo;s block&amp;rdquo; will eventually disappear.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baking papers, or why scientific writing is so difficult</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/why-writing-is-hard/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/why-writing-is-hard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Writing (papers or the dissertation itself) is one of the activities that many doctoral students hate the most. Why is this act of communication so difficult for us? As a prelude to my post on &amp;ldquo;how I write papers&amp;rdquo;, I expose some misconceptions we seem to have about scientific writing and what are good ways to learn it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Risk factors for depression and anxiety in doing a Ph.D.</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a follow-up to &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;the first post in this blog&lt;/a&gt;, I dig a little deeper in some of the research on anxiety and depression during doctoral studies, to find &amp;ldquo;risk factors&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;correlates&amp;rdquo; that seem to often come along these depressive symptoms. I hope that the awareness of these factors (from gender to other things you can actually change in your everyday life) will help you understand why some people struggle doing a PhD, while for others it seems a piece of cake. Change what you do and put the odds on your side!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The second reason why I write this blog</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/second-reason/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/second-reason/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Initially, I thought that I was doing this to help the PhD students around me (and others like them elsewhere) to pass through the dissertation process more effectively, with less stress. But at some point, I realized that other, more selfish, reasons were playing out as well. In this personal account I reflect on a chronic problem of academics and Ph.D. students alike, and how I face it through this blog.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Productivity tip: the Pomodoro technique</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most basic, flexible and effective productivity techniques, which I&amp;rsquo;ve been using for many years.  I know many PhD students and academics that swear by it, but I am still surprised by others who do not know about it. In this post I come back to its origins, how to do it, and how I have combined it with other routines to keep me on track. Essential in this age of smartphones, social media and other constant distractions!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD tool: The CQOCE diagram</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/cqoce-diagram/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/cqoce-diagram/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By far, this is the tool (as in, &amp;ldquo;thinking tool&amp;rdquo;) which I recommend most often to PhD students. This diagram summarizes your main research questions, thesis contributions and evidence of their usefulness. While painful to make, this brutal synthesis exercise is also a powerful communication tool. In this post, I explain how it works, its origins, and how making 18+ versions of it helped me through my PhD. Copy the provided template and use it in your PhD supervision meetings or even in the PhD defense!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is doing a Ph.D. bad... for your mental wellbeing?</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 15:47:47 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a growing body of research that indicates that doing a doctoral dissertation can be taxing on the mental health of PhD students, with depression, anxiety, or burnout as potential pitfalls. Is this problem real and, if so, how bad is it? In this post, I review several recent studies, some of which also offer insights about potential risk factors. This also kickstarts the whole idea of this blog, as a way to increase awareness about these difficulties, and offer practical tips and tricks to survive such a difficult period.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>