<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pages on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/categories/pages/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pages on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 May 2022 07:59:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/categories/pages/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/newsletter/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2022 07:59:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/newsletter/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Happy PhD Toolkit</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/toolkit/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2022 07:59:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/toolkit/</guid>
      <description>Over the years, in the &amp;ldquo;A Happy PhD&amp;rdquo; blog, we have talked about different exercises, structures and templates to support doctoral students in facing multiple challenges along the doctoral journey: from defining the PhD topic to understanding what is important in the doctoral process, or defining the co-author team for a new publication. We are now centralizing all these tools and exercises in a single place, categorized by the problem or need they aim to help with.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 09:59:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/contact/</guid>
      <description>Please leave your comments, suggestions (for future posts or about the blog), etc. in the form below, or email me at ahappyphd.blog@gmail.com. Now you can also leave me a good-old voice message, using the side button on the right.
If you want to be notified by email every time a new post goes up, sign up to the blog&amp;rsquo;s newsletter!
Your NameEmail AddressAn email address is required.Message(function(d){var app = d.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 15:41:55 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/about/</guid>
      <description>About A Happy PhD Are you doing a doctoral dissertation and feeling a bit lost, or unworthy, or just not knowing where to start, how to order your ideas and work effectively? Do you feel like everyone else is finding their path &amp;ldquo;naturally&amp;rdquo;, but you don&amp;rsquo;t?
Are you supervising doctoral students, but feel like you are basically &amp;ldquo;improvising&amp;rdquo;, or following whatever behaviors your advisors applied with you, and wonder why nobody teaches you how to do this, why there is no handbook on how to give effective advice?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>