<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mindfulness on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>http://ahappyphd.org/tags/mindfulness/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mindfulness on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 14:11:06 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ahappyphd.org/tags/mindfulness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Quickie: How to be more mindful</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-mindfulness/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 14:11:06 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/quickie-mindfulness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As our time at home increases due to quarantines and lockdowns, so does our opportunity to endlessly gossip, procrastinate or bitch about the global situation, our leaders and celebrities, or the people we happen to live with. Or, we could choose to be productive. We could choose to develop a new skill. Being mindful allows us to notice, in a non-judgmental way, the richness of life in and around us (yes, even when you’re locked down at home day after day). In this new kind of post (the “quickie”), I give you in brief a few reasons to develop such mindfulness, and three ways to start learning that skill, &lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 4: Resilience</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 19:58:29 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;No matter how meaningful your research feels to you, no matter how engaged you are when doing it, sometimes things just don&amp;rsquo;t work out as you expected. Papers get rejected, proposals are not funded, data gets mangled and needs to be collected again&amp;hellip; plus all the non-research-related stumbling blocks that life throws at us, from sickness to accidents or family tragedies. How fast and how well can we recover from those setbacks that throw us off balance? This fourth post in the series goes over the concept of resilience as an important pillar for staying happy and fulfilled while working in research. Read below for instruments you can use to gauge it, and practices to help you stay resilient in the face of difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>