<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Positive Psychology on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>http://ahappyphd.org/tags/positive-psychology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Positive Psychology on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2019 19:12:54 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ahappyphd.org/tags/positive-psychology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 5: Kindness</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2019 19:12:54 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Even if you feel that your research contributes to a bigger purpose, even if you work at it with great engagement, even if you&amp;rsquo;re resilient to setbacks and misfortune&amp;hellip; still your time working in research can suck. This week I look at the final missing piece in our search for a happier (research) workplace: the quality of our social interactions with others. Particularly, how positive connections and prosocial behaviors can help us &lt;em&gt;thrive&lt;/em&gt; at work (not just survive). In this post, I examine some of the main components of a prosocial workplace, how to assess them for yourself, and a few research-backed practices to make your lab a kinder place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 4: Resilience</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 19:58:29 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;No matter how meaningful your research feels to you, no matter how engaged you are when doing it, sometimes things just don&amp;rsquo;t work out as you expected. Papers get rejected, proposals are not funded, data gets mangled and needs to be collected again&amp;hellip; plus all the non-research-related stumbling blocks that life throws at us, from sickness to accidents or family tragedies. How fast and how well can we recover from those setbacks that throw us off balance? This fourth post in the series goes over the concept of resilience as an important pillar for staying happy and fulfilled while working in research. Read below for instruments you can use to gauge it, and practices to help you stay resilient in the face of difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 3: Engagement</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Sep 2019 19:10:43 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever found yourself avoiding your supervisor, or the thesis meetings, or just not wanting to open the manuscript file you have to finish? Then you might have some problems engaging with your research work. In this third post of the series on finding more happiness in your research, I look at how engagement at work is defined, how to assess your own levels of engagement, and some research-backed practices to help you engage better with your work and find your &amp;ldquo;flow&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 2: Purpose</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2019 09:45:01 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Continuing with last week&amp;rsquo;s post on &amp;ldquo;happiness at work&amp;rdquo;, in this post I explore the first of the four pillars for a happier workplace: the sense that your work has a &lt;em&gt;purpose&lt;/em&gt;, that it is personally meaningful to you. Read on to learn to self-assess your sense of purpose at work, and get some ideas on how to make your research work feel more meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 1: What is happiness?</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 16:43:50 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Being a Ph.D. student and being happy sometimes feel like two incompatible states. However, we all know someone that seems to enjoy greatly their work, even their &lt;em&gt;dissertation&lt;/em&gt; work (heck, I have to confess I&amp;rsquo;ve been one such annoying person myself sometimes). What things make people love their work? Apparently, an entire branch of positive psychology has been delving into this question for decades. This post is the first of a series that adapts insights and practices for greater &amp;ldquo;happiness at work&amp;rdquo; from a massive open online course (MOOC), to the work life of doctoral students (and academics more generally).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>