<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Toolbox on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>http://ahappyphd.org/tags/toolbox/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Toolbox on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 May 2020 11:28:31 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ahappyphd.org/tags/toolbox/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Navigating authorship: a condensed crash course in setting authors for your paper</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/authorship/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2020 11:28:31 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/authorship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Defining who are the authors of your scientific papers, while apparently trivial, is sometimes a surprisingly difficult decision (especially, the first times we do it). As novice researchers, we may operate under conjectures or assumptions about how scientific authorship works, which may not necessarily be true. In this post, I go over several factors that often weigh in into that decision, and I provide a couple of tips and resources about how I would go about taking that decision, ideally.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD tool: Pitching your research with the NABC model</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/pitching-nabc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2019 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/pitching-nabc/</guid>
      <description>As a Ph.D. student, you very often have to present what your research is about. Maybe you want to get quick feedback from a visiting professor. Or you need to give a talk at a conference or doctoral consortium. In this post, I go over a technique adapted from a large US research lab I once visited. I will walk you through its simple four- (or five-)part structure, including real examples from my own work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD tool: The CQOCE diagram</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/cqoce-diagram/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Feb 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/cqoce-diagram/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By far, this is the tool (as in, &amp;ldquo;thinking tool&amp;rdquo;) which I recommend most often to PhD students. This diagram summarizes your main research questions, thesis contributions and evidence of their usefulness. While painful to make, this brutal synthesis exercise is also a powerful communication tool. In this post, I explain how it works, its origins, and how making 18+ versions of it helped me through my PhD. Copy the provided template and use it in your PhD supervision meetings or even in the PhD defense!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>