<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Series on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>http://ahappyphd.org/tags/series/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Series on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 18:59:31 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ahappyphd.org/tags/series/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Making important decisions about the doctorate (I)</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 18:59:31 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/decision-process-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the PhD (and beyond), we sometimes face a difficult situation, and we have to take a hard decision: do I leave my PhD? do I take an unrelated job to earn more money while I try to finish the PhD? do I seek a new supervisor that better supports me? do I accept the change of direction that my supervisor is suggesting? In this two-part post series, I will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; give the answer to those hard questions, but rather provide a decision &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; that can help us find the option that is right &lt;em&gt;for us&lt;/em&gt;, in our particular circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab series</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 16:59:14 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-series/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this blog I have often covered the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/&#34;&gt;mental health&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;wellbeing problems&lt;/a&gt; that may come with doing a PhD, if we are not careful. In this series of posts I look at the flip side of that, diving into the research on &lt;em&gt;thriving&lt;/em&gt; at work, to find out which practices may help us be a little happier during our research, and how to diagnose ourselves about what aspects of our research activity can most be improved.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing research papers series</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/writing-papers-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 16:59:00 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/writing-papers-series/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Writing research papers is one of the most dreaded (and most unavoidable) activities for many people during the PhD. In this series of posts I explore some of the reasons why writing research papers is difficult when one arrives at the PhD, and explain what concrete writing process I find myself following after more than a decade of academic writing.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>