<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Challenges on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>http://ahappyphd.org/tags/challenges/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Challenges on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 19:52:14 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ahappyphd.org/tags/challenges/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The three most common productivity challenges of PhD students</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/productivity-challenges/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 19:52:14 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/productivity-challenges/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you ever feel, during your PhD, that you are not “productive enough”? Guess what, you are not alone. In this post, I share the three most frequently-appearing productivity problems voiced in doctoral workshops we have run in Estonia and Spain. I hope this shows PhD students that they are not alone&amp;hellip; and gives PhD supervisors hints about the hurdles their students often face (whether they mention them explicitly or not). Also, I will give a couple of simple rules to know if these are a problem for you particularly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD tool: Map out your PhD</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/map-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 18:32:52 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/map-thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We know that &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/&#34;&gt;steady everyday progress&lt;/a&gt; is a crucial factor in finishing a PhD. In previous posts, we have seen &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/&#34;&gt;productivity&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/to-do-list-overwhelm/&#34;&gt;techniques&lt;/a&gt; to support us in taking more of these daily steps. Yet, a lot of walking does not necessarily get us anywhere. We need to know that we are actually getting past key reference points, closer to our final destination. In this post, I propose a diagramming exercise to map out key obstacles, milestones and the &amp;ldquo;everyday fuel&amp;rdquo; that propels us past them in our journey towards PhD completion.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>