<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wellbeing on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/wellbeing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Wellbeing on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 12:23:40 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/wellbeing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Reviewing doctoral well-being research (study report)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/review-wellbeing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 12:23:40 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/review-wellbeing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Doctoral well-being is &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/tags/wellbeing/&#34;&gt;one of the central topics in this blog&lt;/a&gt; (indeed, it was the one that &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;started it all&lt;/a&gt;, more than three years ago). While I have tried to base my writings in the peer-reviewed research of this area, so far my reading of it has been rather unsystematic. How do doctoral well-being researchers summarize this body of knowledge? In this post, I distill from the findings of a systematic literature review on doctoral well-being, teasing out topics and factors that we already knew about from previous posts as well as novel ones that we can try to act upon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Avoiding avoidance and other mental self-sabotage in the PhD</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/avoidance/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2022 11:17:22 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/avoidance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Does the thesis bring you a sense of anxiety, fear or discomfort? As we saw &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/am-i-normal/&#34;&gt;in a previous post&lt;/a&gt;, that is not an uncommon experience at certain points during the PhD. At the heart of many of our unsuccessful strategies to deal with these symptoms (including distraction and &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/addiction/&#34;&gt;addiction&lt;/a&gt;) is the notion of avoidance. In this post, we&amp;rsquo;ll explain what avoidance is, its key role in many mental health afflictions, and suggest exercises and strategies to help us overcome these challenges.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Facing addiction to social media in the PhD</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/social-media-addiction/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 23:55:08 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/social-media-addiction/</guid>
      <description>Are you spending more time on social media than you would like? Is your use of Facebook, Twitter, Instagram, TikTok&amp;hellip; hampering progress on your doctoral research? You are not alone: many doctoral students report in our workshops that spending too much time scrolling compulsively on social media is one of their biggest productivity challenges. Building upon the insights about dopamine and addiction from our previous post, here I go over eight concrete steps we can take to break this compulsion and do more of the things we think are really important (like finishing that thesis).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Addiction and the PhD (book extract)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/addiction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Apr 2022 12:06:48 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/addiction/</guid>
      <description>Social media, porn, eating sugary things, shopping, alcohol, or spending our days anxiously reading the news&amp;hellip; Most of us have behaviors or substances we do compulsively, to the point that it damages our relationships and our ability to achieve important goals (including, of course, finishing our PhD thesis). Dopamine is at the heart of these addictions. In this post, I distill lessons learned from reading Anna Lembke&amp;rsquo;s book &amp;ldquo;Dopamine Nation&amp;rdquo;1 about how dopamine works, how to face our addictions, and do more of what we think is important.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quickie: How many PhD students are anxious or depressed (or will drop out) worldwide?</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-many-phd-students/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Sep 2021 13:44:49 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/how-many-phd-students/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the catalysts that kickstarted this blog was the realization that &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;PhD students are at a higher risk of mental health problems&lt;/a&gt; than other students and professionals. Yet, how bad is the problem really? Exactly how many PhD students are &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/am-i-normal/&#34;&gt;suffering&lt;/a&gt; from depression or severe anxiety &lt;em&gt;right now&lt;/em&gt;? How many will &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/drop-out-phd/&#34;&gt;drop out&lt;/a&gt;? In this quickie post, I pull from the data of a few recent studies to give a concrete, numeric &lt;del&gt;answer&lt;/del&gt; guesstimate to these questions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chronobiology addendum: A neurobiologist&#39;s guide to a healthy and productive day</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chronobiology-addendum/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 18:14:20 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chronobiology-addendum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In previous posts, we have seen &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chronobiology/&#34;&gt;how chronotype can influence our productivity&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/chrono-breaks/&#34;&gt;how we can tweak our breaks&lt;/a&gt; to make the most of the ebbs and flows of our daily energy. But, how exactly can we use this chronobiology knowledge to craft a daily routine that is both productive and healthy, and fitting to our particular situation? In this post, I borrow from the habits and routines of an expert on the topic (Stanford neurobiologist Andrew Huberman) ten easy protocols you can put in practice to make every day your best day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Journaling for the doctorate (II): How to journal effectively</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/journaling-tips/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 12:45:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/journaling-tips/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Journaling during your doctorate can have a &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/journaling-benefits/&#34;&gt;host of benefits&lt;/a&gt; (for self-knowledge, mental and physical health). However, not everyone will benefit to the same degree, and different kinds of journaling have different advantages&amp;hellip; if done correctly over a sustained period of time. In this post, I will go over different research-backed journaling exercises and tips to make your journaling most effective.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Journaling for the doctorate (I): Types and benefits</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/journaling-benefits/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Aug 2021 10:40:54 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/journaling-benefits/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you ever get the feeling, at the end of the day, that you have achieved nothing? or that days and weeks pass by, indistinguishable from one another, time slipping away like water between your fingers? Is your mind an unfocused maelstrom of swirling thoughts, ruminating again and again about the same worrying (or plain silly) things? Journaling has been proposed (both by ancient philosophers and modern researchers) as having many benefits, from dealing with stress and trauma, to just understanding ourselves a little better. But, can journaling be useful for us in facing the challenges of a PhD? In this post, I will take a look at the research on different kinds of journaling and what are their effects for mental and physical health.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Monday Mantra to face uncomfortable emotions (#2 productivity challenge sneak peek)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/mantra-emotions/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 08:26:34 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/mantra-emotions/</guid>
      <description>In a previous post, I mentioned that uncomfortable emotions (like guilt, anxiety or indecision) are one of the most common obstacles to productivity that our PhD students report. In preparation for a longer series of posts on &amp;ldquo;emotional first aid for the PhD&amp;rdquo;, I have found a short mental exercise that has helped me face those difficult emotions lately. Here it is, in the form of a card-based &amp;ldquo;Monday Mantra&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Take your holidays… the right way</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/holidays/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 12:01:52 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/holidays/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a PhD student, one sometimes gets the impression that holidays are something that happens only to other people, or that one does not deserve them (I’m so behind on so many things!). Yet, what does the research say about taking holidays, is it really good for you as a doctoral student? Are there better or worse ways of taking a vacation? As preparation for the blog’s own summer hiatus, this post goes over the benefits, pitfalls, and optimal dynamics of taking a longer break.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Am I normal? An intro to mental health in the doctorate</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/am-i-normal/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 09:04:40 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/am-i-normal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;By now, we have established that PhD students (and academics in general) &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;seem to be at a higher risk to develop mental health problems&lt;/a&gt; like depression or chronic stress. But, how can we know if &lt;em&gt;we&lt;/em&gt; have one of these mental health problems, right here, right now? In this post, co-authored with colleague, friend and therapist Paula Odriozola-González, we go over a few basic concepts of psychopathology, and propose criteria and simple practices to help separate internal experiences that we all go through at one time or another, from the more serious stuff.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Sleep</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/on-sleep/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2020 20:34:26 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/on-sleep/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Is your PhD giving you beautiful dreams or horrible nightmares? In either case, you probably should be getting more of them. Sleep (or, rather, lack of sleep) is one of the best-known and most consistent &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/&#34;&gt;risk factors related to depression, anxiety&lt;/a&gt;, and host of other mental and physical health issues. It is also one of the factors (mostly) under our control &amp;ndash; even if it often gets the back seat with respect to other priorities like work, social life, family, or the latest season of our favorite TV show. In this post, I review some of the (very extense, and rather terrifying) research about the effects that lack of sleep has on humans in general, and PhD students in particular. The post also points you to practices and resources to help you in sleeping not only longer, but also better. Keep your delicate mind and body machinery in optimal working condition!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultivating the progress loop in your PhD</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 11:30:48 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt like you are &amp;ldquo;stuck&amp;rdquo; in your PhD, making no progress, or going in circles? If so, you are in good company &amp;ndash; most PhD students report such experience at one time or another during their doctoral process. The normalcy of this experience, however, should not make us dismiss it as unimportant. In this post I review research that speaks to the importance of this sense of progress (or the lack of it) to our engagement with work and the eventual completion (or dropping out) of the PhD. The post also reviews several everyday practices to cultivate your own sense of progress.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab series</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-series/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 16:59:14 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-series/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this blog I have often covered the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/&#34;&gt;mental health&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;wellbeing problems&lt;/a&gt; that may come with doing a PhD, if we are not careful. In this series of posts I look at the flip side of that, diving into the research on &lt;em&gt;thriving&lt;/em&gt; at work, to find out which practices may help us be a little happier during our research, and how to diagnose ourselves about what aspects of our research activity can most be improved.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 5: Kindness</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2019 19:12:54 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Even if you feel that your research contributes to a bigger purpose, even if you work at it with great engagement, even if you&amp;rsquo;re resilient to setbacks and misfortune&amp;hellip; still your time working in research can suck. This week I look at the final missing piece in our search for a happier (research) workplace: the quality of our social interactions with others. Particularly, how positive connections and prosocial behaviors can help us &lt;em&gt;thrive&lt;/em&gt; at work (not just survive). In this post, I examine some of the main components of a prosocial workplace, how to assess them for yourself, and a few research-backed practices to make your lab a kinder place.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 4: Resilience</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 19:58:29 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;No matter how meaningful your research feels to you, no matter how engaged you are when doing it, sometimes things just don&amp;rsquo;t work out as you expected. Papers get rejected, proposals are not funded, data gets mangled and needs to be collected again&amp;hellip; plus all the non-research-related stumbling blocks that life throws at us, from sickness to accidents or family tragedies. How fast and how well can we recover from those setbacks that throw us off balance? This fourth post in the series goes over the concept of resilience as an important pillar for staying happy and fulfilled while working in research. Read below for instruments you can use to gauge it, and practices to help you stay resilient in the face of difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 3: Engagement</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Sep 2019 19:10:43 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever found yourself avoiding your supervisor, or the thesis meetings, or just not wanting to open the manuscript file you have to finish? Then you might have some problems engaging with your research work. In this third post of the series on finding more happiness in your research, I look at how engagement at work is defined, how to assess your own levels of engagement, and some research-backed practices to help you engage better with your work and find your &amp;ldquo;flow&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 2: Purpose</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2019 09:45:01 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Continuing with last week&amp;rsquo;s post on &amp;ldquo;happiness at work&amp;rdquo;, in this post I explore the first of the four pillars for a happier workplace: the sense that your work has a &lt;em&gt;purpose&lt;/em&gt;, that it is personally meaningful to you. Read on to learn to self-assess your sense of purpose at work, and get some ideas on how to make your research work feel more meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness in the lab, part 1: What is happiness?</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 16:43:50 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Being a Ph.D. student and being happy sometimes feel like two incompatible states. However, we all know someone that seems to enjoy greatly their work, even their &lt;em&gt;dissertation&lt;/em&gt; work (heck, I have to confess I&amp;rsquo;ve been one such annoying person myself sometimes). What things make people love their work? Apparently, an entire branch of positive psychology has been delving into this question for decades. This post is the first of a series that adapts insights and practices for greater &amp;ldquo;happiness at work&amp;rdquo; from a massive open online course (MOOC), to the work life of doctoral students (and academics more generally).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On cultivating (and reining) curiosity</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/cultivate-curiosity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2019 01:01:58 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/cultivate-curiosity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One would think that research, as the pursuit of new knowledge, is mostly based upon curiosity. However, the daily grind of research life can erode that sense of excitement students have about delving into the unknown. In this post, I explore the role of curiosity in doctoral studies, and look at a few practices and tricks to keep the flame of curiosity alight (without burning the village!).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Choosing not to drop out: a view from self-determination theory</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/choosing-not-drop-out/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/choosing-not-drop-out/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/drop-out-phd/&#34;&gt;last week&amp;rsquo;s post&lt;/a&gt;, we established that dropping out of a Ph.D. (or thinking about it) is surprisingly common, and we saw demographic and socio-economic factors that seem related to doctoral attrition. In this post, I dive into another strand of research that relates doctoral dropout with a general theory of human motivation: &lt;em&gt;self-determination theory&lt;/em&gt;. This research helps explain why you may persist and finish your doctorate (and even have fun doing it), despite having such socio-economic factors playing against you. Or vice-versa. The post also gleans practical advice from the literature on doctoral attrition, in the hope of helping students and supervisors avoid this common pitfall.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who drops out of the Ph.D.?</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/drop-out-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/drop-out-phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Aside from the fact that doing a Ph.D. &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;seems to put you at a greater risk of being anxious or depressed&lt;/a&gt; than other occupations, some students may also face the question: will I ever finish my thesis &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;? This post digs into research about doctoral attrition and completion, and what factors seem to make dropping out more likely. Do not give up!&amp;hellip; unless you really want to.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Risk factors for depression and anxiety in doing a Ph.D.</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/risk-factors-phd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a follow-up to &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/&#34;&gt;the first post in this blog&lt;/a&gt;, I dig a little deeper in some of the research on anxiety and depression during doctoral studies, to find &amp;ldquo;risk factors&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;correlates&amp;rdquo; that seem to often come along these depressive symptoms. I hope that the awareness of these factors (from gender to other things you can actually change in your everyday life) will help you understand why some people struggle doing a PhD, while for others it seems a piece of cake. Change what you do and put the odds on your side!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The second reason why I write this blog</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/second-reason/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/second-reason/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Initially, I thought that I was doing this to help the PhD students around me (and others like them elsewhere) to pass through the dissertation process more effectively, with less stress. But at some point, I realized that other, more selfish, reasons were playing out as well. In this personal account I reflect on a chronic problem of academics and Ph.D. students alike, and how I face it through this blog.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is doing a Ph.D. bad... for your mental wellbeing?</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jan 2019 15:47:47 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/is-phd-bad-mental-wellbeing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a growing body of research that indicates that doing a doctoral dissertation can be taxing on the mental health of PhD students, with depression, anxiety, or burnout as potential pitfalls. Is this problem real and, if so, how bad is it? In this post, I review several recent studies, some of which also offer insights about potential risk factors. This also kickstarts the whole idea of this blog, as a way to increase awareness about these difficulties, and offer practical tips and tricks to survive such a difficult period.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>