<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Productivity on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>http://ahappyphd.org/tags/productivity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Productivity on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2020 09:46:51 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://ahappyphd.org/tags/productivity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Advising for progress: tips for PhD supervisors</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/advising-progress/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2020 09:46:51 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/advising-progress/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/&#34;&gt;a previous post&lt;/a&gt;, we have seen the crucial role that having a sense of progress plays, not only in the productivity, but also in the engagement and persistence of a PhD student towards the doctorate. While this recognition (and the practices to &amp;ldquo;make progress visible&amp;rdquo; we saw) put a big emphasis on the student as the main active agent, PhD students are not the only actors in this play. Is there anything that doctoral &lt;em&gt;supervisors&lt;/em&gt; can do to help? In this post, I go over some of the same management research on progress and our own evidence from the field, looking at what supervisors can do to support their students in perceiving continuous progress that eventually leads to a finished doctoral thesis.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultivating the progress loop in your PhD</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2020 11:30:48 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/progress-loop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt like you are &amp;ldquo;stuck&amp;rdquo; in your PhD, making no progress, or going in circles? If so, you are in good company &amp;ndash; most PhD students report such experience at one time or another during their doctoral process. The normalcy of this experience, however, should not make us dismiss it as unimportant. In this post I review research that speaks to the importance of this sense of progress (or the lack of it) to our engagement with work and the eventual completion (or dropping out) of the PhD. The post also reviews several everyday practices to cultivate your own sense of progress.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday Mantra #4: On attention</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2019 10:49:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ability to pay attention is one of the most important assets of a PhD student (or researcher) and plays a crucial role on our focus and productivity, but also on our creativity and wellbeing. In this month&#39;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-1/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Monday Mantra&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, I give you not one, but &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; sentences that you can use to remind yourself to manage this resource wisely. Choose your favorite!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report from the trenches: of calendar tricks and time scarcity</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/calendar-trick/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 17:41:51 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/calendar-trick/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/to-do-list-overwhelm/&#34;&gt;a previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I proposed the use of your favorite calendar app to store all your TO-DOs and avoid over-committing. I&#39;ve been trying this productivity trick on myself for the past few months. In this new kind of blog post, I report on the results of this self-experiment, and the effect it has had on my own productivity and wellbeing. I also provide some practical tips and tricks, in case you want to try it out for yourself. &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Too_long;_didn%27t_read&#34;&gt;TL;DR&lt;/a&gt;: It works&amp;hellip; if you are a bit careful.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Productivity tip: How I do weekly reviews</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/weekly-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2019 12:54:50 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/weekly-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Despite the emphasis I have made so far in developing productive and healthy everyday routines (from &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/to-do-list-overwhelm/&#34;&gt;to-do lists&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/&#34;&gt;pomodoros&lt;/a&gt;), not everything about productivity happens at this tactical, day-to-day level. In this short post, I guide you through what I think is the centerpiece of my own personal productivity system: the weekly review.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday mantra #3: When you have too many open fronts</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 17:01:51 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever felt that you have too many threads open in your research work, and you cannot seem to make substantial progress in any of them? You are not alone. After closing the long series of posts on &lt;a href=&#34;http://ahappyphd.org/posts/happiness-in-the-lab-series/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;happiness in the lab&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, a bit of a lighter read this week. In this post I give very short advice that you can use as a &amp;ldquo;mantra&amp;rdquo; for this and the coming weeks, somewhat related to staying productive &amp;ndash; but with a twist.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A small hiatus, and a Monday Mantra</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2019 21:28:44 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A shorter post this week, to warn you about a small hiatus in the blog (due to taking a &amp;ldquo;disconnected break&amp;rdquo;), and to propose a new post format: Monday Mantras. As the first exercise in this format, I propose you use the best shortest productivity advice I&#39;ve ever read.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to deal with to-do list overwhelm</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/to-do-list-overwhelm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/to-do-list-overwhelm/</guid>
      <description>The to-do list is an essential staple of an organized, reliable doctoral student (or academic). Yet, have you ever looked at your task list and felt anxious, certain that you have too much to do and too little time? In this post, I review several routines that have helped me overcome this ubiquitous feeling.
I have been working (in the industry and in academia) for about twenty years now. Yet, periodically, I look at my to-do list, or at the list of “projects I’m doing”, and I feel my heart rate rise.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Productivity tip: the Pomodoro technique</title>
      <link>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Feb 2019 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://ahappyphd.org/posts/pomodoro-technique/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most basic, flexible and effective productivity techniques, which I&#39;ve been using for many years.  I know many PhD students and academics that swear by it, but I am still surprised by others who do not know about it. In this post I come back to its origins, how to do it, and how I have combined it with other routines to keep me on track. Essential in this age of smartphones, social media and other constant distractions!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>