<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Attention on A Happy PhD</title>
    <link>https://ahappyphd.org/tags/attention/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Attention on A Happy PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 09:52:37 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ahappyphd.org/tags/attention/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Two Hundred Weeks: Productivity for Mortal PhD Students (book extract)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/productivity-mortal-phds/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 09:52:37 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/productivity-mortal-phds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Is there a way to be productive in our PhD without falling into all-out work obsession and burnout? What habits and systems could help us make good use of our (inherently limited) time and effort, taking into account that we could die tomorrow? In this second part of our &lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.to/3vGOcvE&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Four Thousand Weeks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; book summary, we look at some of the tactical and strategic advice stemming from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/productivity-avoidance/&#34;&gt;productivity mindset shifts&lt;/a&gt; the book suggests &amp;ndash; filtered and contextualized for doctoral students aware of their finitude.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quickie: Preloading productive meditation (book extract)</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/preloading/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2022 08:42:03 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/preloading/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We have established that &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/scheduling-strategies/&#34;&gt;finding long periods of time&lt;/a&gt; for deep, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/create-consume/&#34;&gt;creative&lt;/a&gt; research tasks (be it writing a paper or designing our next study) is critical to achieve our thesis &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/map-thesis/&#34;&gt;milestones&lt;/a&gt; and finish the PhD. Yet, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/execution/&#34;&gt;we are all very busy&lt;/a&gt; and have limited time for such creativity. To help in solving this conundrum, this short post describes a technique I&amp;rsquo;ve been using lately to squeeze a few extra hours a week to make headway in those hard, creative research tasks.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Monday Mantra #4: On attention</title>
      <link>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2019 10:49:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The ability to pay attention is one of the most important assets of a PhD student (or researcher) and plays a crucial role on our focus and productivity, but also on our creativity and wellbeing. In this month&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://ahappyphd.org/posts/monday-mantra-1/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Monday Mantra&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, I give you not one, but &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; sentences that you can use to remind yourself to manage this resource wisely. Choose your favorite!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>